阿 拉 伯 的 劳 伦 斯
*^^* 第35届奥斯卡(1963年) 最佳影片*^^*
警告
危险
1888-1935
T.E.劳伦斯
He was the most extraordinary man I ever knew.
他是我认识的人当中 最不平凡的一个人
Did you know him well?
你跟他很熟吗？
I knew him.
我认识他
Well, nil nisi bonum.
你要不就是跟他很熟 要不就是不认识他
But did he really deserve...
但他真的值得…
...a place in here?
你们把他葬在这里吗？
Lord Allenby, could you give a few words about Lawrence?
阿兰比大人 你能谈谈劳伦斯吗？
What, more words?
什么？还要再说啊？
The revolt in the desert...
沙漠的叛乱事件…
...played a decisive part in the Middle Eastern campaign.
在中东局势中 扮演着决定性的角色
Yes, sir, but about Colonel Lawrence himself.
是的，但我想请您 谈谈劳伦斯上校这个人
No, no. I didn't know him well, you know.
不，我跟他不熟，你知道的
Mr. Bentley, you know as much about Lawrence as anybody.
班特尼先生，你可说是最认识劳伦斯
Yes, it was my privilege to know him.
是的，能认识他…
And to make him known to the world.
跟让世人认识他，是我的荣幸
He was a poet, a scholar and a mighty warrior.
他是诗人，学者及英勇的战士
Thank you.
谢谢
He was also the most shameless exhibitionist since Barnum and Bailey.
他还是自从巴纳姆跟贝利之后 最无耻的爱现狂
You, sir. Who are you?
您是哪位？
My name is Jackson Bentley.
我是杰克森班特利
I overheard your last remark and take the gravest exception.
我听到你刚说的话 并对那提出最严重的异议
- He was a great man. - Did you know him?
- 他是个伟大的人 - 你认识他吗？
No, I can't claim to have known him.
不，我不能说我认识他
I had the honour to shake his hand in Damascus.
我很荣幸在大马士革跟他握过手
Knew him? I never knew him.
认识他？我从来都不认识他
He had some minor function on my staff in Cairo.
他曾在开罗为我做些不重要工作
Michael George Hartley...
麦克乔治哈特利
...this is a nasty, dark little room.
这是个又脏又暗的小房间
That's right.
没错
We are not happy in it.
我们在这里不快乐
I am. It's better than a nasty, dark little trench.
我快乐，这要比待在 又脏又暗的的小战壕来得好
- Then you're a big noble fellow. - That's right.
- 那么你是个高尚的贵族啰 - 没错
Here is William Potter with my newspaper.
威廉波特拿着我的报纸来了
- Here you are, tosh. - Thanks.
- 拿去吧 - 谢谢
Would you care for one of Corporal Hartley's cigarettes?
你想来根哈特利上校的香烟吗？
- Is it there? - Of course.
- 有刊登吗？ - 当然有
Headlines.
头条新闻
But I bet it isn't mentioned in the Times.
我敢说泰晤士时报 一定没提这条新闻
"Bedouin tribes attack Turkish stronghold."
“贝都因人攻击土耳其要塞”
I bet that no one in this headquarters even knows it happened.
我敢说连这里总部的人 都不知道这件事
Or would care if it did. Allow me to ignite your cigarette.
或者在乎这件事，我来帮你点烟
- Mr. Lawrence? - Yes.
- 劳伦斯先生？ - 我就是
- Flimsy, sir. - Thank you.
- 您的电报 - 谢谢
You'll do that once too often. It's only flesh and blood.
你总有一次会闯祸的 只不过是血肉罢了
Michael George Hartley, you're a philosopher.
麦克乔治哈特利 你是个哲学家
And you're balmy!
你是个怪人！
- It damn well hurts! - Certainly, it hurts.
- 好痛啊！ - 当然会痛啰
What's the trick, then?
那么秘诀是什么？
The trick, William Potter, is not minding that it hurts.
威廉波特 秘诀就是不要在乎会痛
By the way, if Captain Gibbon should enquire for me...
还有如果吉普森上尉要找我
...tell him I've gone for a chat with the general.
告诉他我去跟将军聊天了
- He's balmy. - He's all right.
- 他是个怪人 - 他很正常
Lawrence.
劳伦斯
Yes?
什么事？
You're supposed to be...
你应该要…
Do you usually wear your cap in the mess?
你通常都是那样戴着 帽子进来这里的吗？
Always.
我一直都是这样
You should be on duty. Where are you going?
你应该在当班 你要去哪里？
Mustn't talk shop, Freddie, not in the mess.
别跟我说教 佛莱迪，这里是休息室啊
I'm going for a powwow with the general.
我要去跟将军谈一谈
I'm not asking as your superior, but as the secretary of this mess.
我不是以长官的身份问你 而是以休息室负责人身份在问你
We don't want chaps in here who should be on duty.
我们不要该在当班的人进来
Where are you going?
请告诉我，你要去哪里？
I must say, Lawrence!
我得警告你，劳伦斯！
- Sorry. - You're a clown, Lawrence.
- 抱歉 - 你是个小丑，劳伦斯
Ah, well, we can't all be lion tamers.
不可能人人都是驯兽师
Sorry.
抱歉
It's an intrigue, Dryden.
真是个谜，戴登
I do not propose to let an overweening, crass lieutenant...
我不建议让一个自大愚蠢的中尉
...thumb his nose at his commander and get away with it.
对指挥官的命令不屑一顾 而且还不受到惩罚
It doesn't sound as though he'd be any great loss, sir.
听起来没有他不是任何大损失
Don't try that, Dryden. There's a principle involved.
别那么做，戴登，这是原则问题
There is, indeed.
没错
He's of no use here in Cairo.
他待在开罗一点用处都没有
He might be in Arabia. He knows his stuff, sir.
他或许该到阿拉伯去 他清楚时事，长官
Knows the books, you mean.
你是说他清楚那本书吧
I've already sent out Colonel Brighton, who's a soldier.
我已经派布莱顿上校去了 他是一位士兵
If Brighton thinks we should send some arms, we will.
如果布莱顿认为我们该出兵 我们会那么做的
Well, what more do you want?
你还需要什么？
That there would be no question of Lieutenant Lawrence...
你确定劳伦斯中尉…
...giving military advice.
不会给任何军事上的建议
By God, I should hope not.
天啊，我希望他不会那么做
It's just that the Arab Bureau would like its own man on the spot to...
只是阿拉伯局 希望有自己的人在现场…
To what?
做什么？
To make our own appraisal of the situation.
给我们作一个评估
I'll tell you, it's my considered opinion and that of my staff...
我还要告诉你 这是我跟我手下的意见
...that time spent on the Bedouin will be time wasted.
任何花在贝都因人身上的时间 都是浪费了的时间
They're a nation of sheep- stealers.
他们是一个偷羊贼的民族
They did attack Medina.
他们的确攻击了麦地纳
And the Turks made mincemeat of them.
土耳其人把他们打的粉身碎骨
We don't know that.
我们不知道这件事
We know that they didn't take it. A storm in a teacup, a sideshow.
我们知道他们没接受 那没什么，只是段小插曲
In my opinion, this whole theatre of operations is a sideshow.
如果你想听我的意见 我觉得这儿根本是个小插曲
The real war's being fought against Germans, not Turks.
真正的战争敌人是德国人 不是土耳其人
Not here, but on the Western front in the trenches.
战场不在这里而是在西线
Your Bedouin Army, or whatever it calls itself...
你的贝都因军队 不管他们是如何称呼自己
...would be a sideshow of a sideshow.
他们只不过是一段小插曲中的小配角
Big things have small beginnings, sir.
伟大的事都是 从很小的开端开始的，长官
Does the Arab Bureau want a big thing in Arabia?
阿拉伯局希望阿拉伯发生大事吗？
Does the bureau think they'll sit down under us when this war is over?
在战争结束后 他们会臣服于我们之下吗？
The bureau thinks the job of the moment, sir, is to win the war.
长官，局里认为 现在的工作是要打胜仗
Don't tell me my duty, Mr. Dryden.
别告诉我我有什么责任，戴登先生
- Lawrence, sir. - Send him in.
- 劳伦斯来了，长官 - 请他进来
Good morning, sir.
早安
Salute.
敬礼
If you're insubordinate, I shall put you under arrest.
如果你要抗命，我会逮捕你的
- It's my manner. - Your what?
- 是我的态度 - 你的什么？
My manner. It looks insubordinate, but it isn't.
长官，我的态度看来像是抗命 但事实上却不然
I can't make out whether you're bad- mannered or just half- witted.
我弄不清楚 你是态度恶劣或是愚蠢
- I have the same problem, sir. - Shut up.
- 我也有相同的问题，长官 - 闭嘴
The Arab Bureau thinks you would be of use to them in Arabia.
阿拉伯局认为你在阿拉伯 应该会派上用场了
Why, I can't imagine.
我真想不到什么原因
You can't perform your present duties properly.
你无法完成你现在的任务
"I cannot fiddle, but I can make a great state from a little city."
“我不会拉提琴，但我能让一个 小城市变成一个伟大的国家”
- What? - Themistocles, sir.
- 什么？ - 那是希米斯特克拉斯的话
- A Greek philosopher. - I know you've been well- educated.
- 他是希腊的哲学家 - 我知道你受过高深的教育
It says so in your dossier.
你的档案上是那么说的
You're the kind of creature I can't stand, Lawrence.
你是我受不了的那种人 劳伦斯
But I suppose I could be wrong.
但我想我可能错了
All right, Dryden. You can have him for six weeks.
好了，戴丹 你可以把他带走六星期
Who knows? It might even make a man of him. Come in!
谁知道呢？或许可以把他 变成男子汉，进来！
Yes, what is it?
什么事？
The convoy will be in Port Said tomorrow night.
舰队明天晚上会到赛德港
- Is that certain? - Yes, sir.
- 确定了吗？ - 是的，长官
There doesn't seem to be any artillery.
看来似乎没有大炮
But there must be artillery!
但应该要有才对啊！
Sir, this is something of an expedition.
长官，他要去很远的地方
He has to get to Yenbo, find a guide, find the Arabs and then get back.
他得到阳波去找向导 找到阿拉伯人然后回来
He can't do that in six weeks.
他在六星期内是办不到的
- Two months, then. - Three.
- 那么就两个月吧 - 三个月
All right, three. Now, will you let me do some work, Mr. Dryden?
好吧，三个月，好了 可以让我做点工作了吗？戴丹
Thank you, sir.
谢谢您，长官
I'd like to say, sir, that I am grateful for this.
我想说的是我很高兴 您做了这样的决定
Shut up and get out.
闭上你的嘴，快滚出去
Sir?
长官
How can I fight a bloody war without bloody artillery?
没有该死的大炮 我要怎么打赢一场战争？
- How did you do it? - Might better ask why I bothered to.
- 你是怎么办到？ - 你该问我干嘛这么为你费心
- Because I'm the man for the job. - I just wonder about that.
- 因为我是最合适的人 - 我真不知道
Of course I am. What is the job, by the way?
我当然是啰 对了，任务内容是什么？
Find Prince Feisal.
去找费瑟王子
Good. And when I've found him?
好，找到他之后呢？
Find out what kind of a man he is.
查出他是什么样的人
Find out what his intentions are. Not his immediate intentions.
查出他有什么企图 不是立即的企图
That is Colonel Brighton's business, not yours.
那是布莱顿上校的事 不是你的事
I mean, his intentions in Arabia altogether.
我是说他在阿拉伯所有的企图
That's new.
那可新奇了
Where are they now?
他们现在在哪里？
Anywhere within 300 miles of Medina.
在麦地纳方圆三百里内
They're Hashemite Bedouins.
他们是哈希米特贝都因人
They can cross 60 miles of desert in a day.
他们可以在一天内 在沙漠中行走六十里
Thanks. This is going to be fun.
谢谢你，戴丹，这一定会很有趣
Lawrence, only two kinds of creature get fun in the desert:
劳伦斯，沙漠里只有 两种人物可以享乐
Bedouins and gods, and you're neither. Take it from me.
就是贝都因人跟神，你两者都不是 记住我的话
For ordinary men, it's a burning fiery furnace.
对普通人来说 那里像是个炙热的火炉
No, Dryden. It's going to be fun.
不，戴丹，一定会很好玩的
It is recognized that you have a funny sense of fun.
大家都认为你的幽默感很有趣
Here you may drink.
你可以在这里喝点水
One cup.
一杯就好
You do not drink?
你不喝？
No.
我不要
I'll drink when you do.
你喝我才喝
I am Bedu.
我是贝都因人
Truly, now, you are a British officer?
告诉我 你真的是英国军官吗？
Yes.
是的
From Cairo?
你来自开罗？
Yes.
对
- You did not ride from Cairo? - No.
- 你不是从开罗骑骆鸵来的？ - 不是
Thank heaven. It's 900 miles. I came by boat.
谢天谢地，那可有九百里远啊 我是搭船来的
And before?
之前呢？
From Britain?
英国来的？
Yes.
对
Truly?
真的吗？
From Oxfordshire.
我来自牛津夏尔
Is that a desert country?
那是沙漠地带吗？
No. A fat country. Fat people.
不，那是个富裕的国家 每个人都很富裕
You are not fat?
你不是？
No.
对
I'm different.
我不一样
Here...
好了
...take it.
拿去
First I take you to Lord Feisal, then you give it to me.
我先带你去找费瑟殿下 你再把它交给我
Take it now.
现在就拿去吧
Bedu food.
贝都因食物
Good.
很好吃
More?
还要吗？
- Bedu. - Where?
- 贝都因人 - 哪里？
From here to Lord Feisal's camp is Harith country.
从这里到费瑟殿下的营地 是哈利斯国
Yes, I know.
对，我知道
- I am not Harith. - No.
- 我不是哈利斯人 - 对
Hazimi, of the Beni Salem.
贝尼沙伦的哈齐尼人
Put the right foot in tight. Lock it with your left foot.
右腿靠拢，用左腿钩着
When you are ready to go...
当你准备好要走了…
...hit her on the shoulder and say, "Hut- hut- hut."
打它的肩膀说“哈，哈，哈”
Today will be difficult, but tomorrow, good riding.
今天会很辛苦 但明天的行程就轻松了
I think we reach Masturah Well tomorrow. Yes.
我想我们明天 应该能到马斯杜拉水井
And from Masturah Well to Lord Feisal's camp, one day more.
从马斯杜拉水井到费瑟殿下 的营地还要一天的路程
Now!
快！
Good?
还好吗？
It's all right.
还不错
This is a Harith well.
这是哈利斯的水井
The Harith are a dirty people.
哈利斯的人很脏
Turks?
是土耳其人吗？
Bedu.
是贝都因人
Who is he?
他是谁？
He is dead.
他死了
Yes.
对
Why?
为什么？
This is my well.
这是我的水井
I have drunk from it.
我从这里取水喝
You are welcome.
我欢迎你喝
He was my friend.
他是我的朋友
- That? - Yes, that.
- 那个吗？ - 对，那个
- This pistol yours? - No, his.
- 这把手枪是你的吗？ - 不，是他的
His?
是他的？
Mine.
是我的
Then I will use it.
那我要把它拿来用
Your friend...
你的朋友
...was a Hazimi of the Beni Salem.
贝尼沙伦的哈齐尼人
I know.
我知道
I am Ali ibn el Kharish.
我是阿里伊本艾卡利希
I have heard of you.
我听说过你
So...
好了
...what was a Hazimi doing here?
一个哈齐尼人在这里做什么？
He was taking me to help Prince Feisal.
他要带我去帮助费瑟王子
- You've been sent from Cairo. - Yes.
- 你是开罗那边派来的人 - 对
I have been in Cairo for my schooling.
我是在开罗念书的
I can both read and write.
我会读跟写
My Lord Feisal already has an Englishman.
费瑟殿下已经有个英国绅士了
What is your name?
你叫什么名字？
My name is for my friends.
我的名字只告诉朋友
None of my friends is a murderer.
我的朋友都不会杀人
You are angry, English.
你在生气，英国人
He was nothing.
他什么都不是
The well is everything.
这口水井就是一切
The Hazimi may not drink at our wells.
哈齐尼人 不许喝我们水井里的水
He knew that.
他知道的
Salaam.
你好
Sherif Ali.
阿里长官
So long as the Arabs fight tribe against tribe...
只要阿拉伯的部族战争不休
...so long will they be a little people...
他们仍是一个弱小的民族
...a silly people.
一个愚蠢的民族
Greedy, barbarous and cruel, as you are.
跟你一样贪婪，野蛮跟残忍
Come.
来吧
I will take you to Feisal.
我带你去见费瑟
I do not want your company, sherif.
我不要你陪我一起去，长官
Wadi Safra is another day from here.
万迪沙法拉离这里 还要一天的路程
You will not find it, and you will die.
你到不了那里的 到不了那里你就死定了
I will find it with this.
有了这个，我到得了那里
Good army compass.
很棒的军队罗盘
How if I take it?
我把它拿走会怎么样？
Then you would be a thief.
那你就是小偷
Have you no fear, English?
你不怕吗？英国人
My fear is my concern.
怕不怕是我的问题
Truly.
真的
God be with you, English.
愿真主与你同在，英国人
As I walk along the Bois de Boulogne With an independent air
当我自力地走在波斯迪波兰尼
You can hear the girls declare
你可以听到女孩子们说
He must be a millionaire
他一定是百万富翁
I'm the man who broke the bank At Monte Carlo
我在蒙地卡罗赢光了他们的钱
Hey, you!
嘿，你！
- I've been waiting for you. - Did you know I was coming?
- 我一直在等你 - 你知道我会来？
I knew someone was coming. Feisal told me.
我知道有人会来 费瑟告诉我的
How did he know?
他怎么会知道？
Not much happens within 50 miles of Feisal that he doesn't know.
方圆五十里发生的事 没有一件是费瑟不知道的
I'll give him that. No escort?
我相信，没有人陪你来？
My guide was killed at the Masturah Well.
我的向导在马斯杜拉水井被杀了
- Turks? - No, an Arab.
- 土耳其人杀的？ - 不，他是阿拉伯人
Bloody savages.
残忍的野蛮人
- This is Wadi Safra, isn't it? - Yes, they're over there.
- 这里是万迪沙法拉，对吧？ - 对，他们在那边
Just a minute. What's your name and who sent you?
等一下，你叫什么名字？ 是谁派你来的？
Lawrence. I've been seconded to the Arab Bureau.
我是劳伦斯 我隶属于阿拉伯局
What are you to do for the Arab Bureau?
你在为阿拉伯局做什么？
Well, it's rather vague, sir. I'm to appreciate the situation.
不是很清楚 我是来了解这儿的状况
Well, that won't be difficult. The situation's bloody awful.
那一点都不难，情况非常可怕
Their morale, if they ever had any, which I doubt...
他们的士气 我怀疑他们是否有士气
...the Turks knocked out of them in front of Medina, with howitzers.
土耳其人在麦地纳前 用榴弹炮击溃了他们
They're fading away by dozens every night.
他们每晚都有好几十个跑掉
What I want to say is this:
这是我想说的：
Wherever you are and whoever you are with...
不管你在哪里 还有你跟谁在一起
...you're a British officer. Here's an order.
你仍是英国军官，这是命令
When we get into that camp, you're to keep your mouth shut.
当我们进入营地时 你得把嘴巴闭上
- Do you understand what I'm saying? - I understand what you're saying.
- 你知道我在说什么吗？ - 我知道你在说什么
You'll make your appreciation and get back to...
你了解好了以后就回到…
Oh, my God.
天啊
Not again.
别又来了
I've told him! God knows I've told him.
我告诉过他了 天知道，我告诉过他了
"Move South," I've said. "You're still in range."
我说“往南走 你还在射击范围内”
They simply will not understand what modern weapons do!
他们根本不了解 现在武器的威力！
Stand and fight. Stand and fight.
挺身而战！
Fire back at them.
向他们还击！
- Who are you? - Lieutenant Lawrence, sir.
- 你是谁？ - 劳伦斯中尉，长官
Seconded to the Arab Bureau.
我隶属于阿拉伯局
This is a bloody mess, sir. We'll have to move south.
这真的是一团乱 我们真的得往南走
Yes, colonel, 50 miles south.
是的，上校，往南走五十里
You were right and I was wrong.
你说的对，我错了
We must take some thought for the wounded.
我们得想想如何处理伤者
- We can take care of them at Yenbo. - Lf they can get to Yenbo.
- 我们可以到阳波帮他们疗伤 - 只要他们到得了阳波
They can hardly come with us.
他们不可能跟我们一起走
No. They must try to reach Yenbo. Lieutenant...?
不，他们得试着到阳波去 那个…？
Lawrence.
劳伦斯
You understand, Lieutenant Lawrence...
你明白的，劳伦斯中尉
...my people are unused to explosives and machines.
我的人不习惯炸药跟机器
First the guns, and now this.
先是枪，现在又是这个
Cigarette?
有香烟吗？
I'm sorry.
抱歉
Cigarette, Your Excellency?
有烟吗？殿下
Umph off.
走开
Please, Your Excellency. Just one for two?
拜托，殿下 就给我们两个人一根烟？
Hold it, Jenkins!
等一下，贾金斯！
Jenkins!
贾金斯！
Lawrence?
劳伦斯？
You have no servant.
你没有带随从
- I don't need a servant. - No?
- 我不需要随从 - 是吗？
We can do everything. Light fires, cook food, wash clothes.
我们什么都会做 生火，煮食物，洗衣服
- Yes, everything. - I don't doubt it.
- 对，什么都会做 - 我不怀疑
- It will be very nice for you. - I can't afford it.
- 那对你来说是件好事 - 我负担不起
Recite, then, as much of the Koran as may be easy to you.
那么尽可能地朗读古兰经吧
God knoweth that there be some among you sick...
天知道你们当中有些病人
...while others travel through the Earth in quest for the bounties of God.
其他人在世界到处旅行 寻找真主的恩赐
Others do battle in His cause.
其他人为祂而战
Recite, therefore, as much as may be easy.
所以尽可能地朗读吧
And observe the prayers.
服从经文
This will be best and richest in the recompense.
这将会是最好 最丰硕的报答
Seek ye the forgiveness of God.
寻求真主的宽恕
Verily, God is forgiving, merciful...
真主是会原谅你 祂是那么地仁慈…
Greetings, Ali.
你好啊，阿里
- My lord. - Sherif Ali.
- 殿下 - 阿里长官
Lieutenant Lawrence, you have met Sherif Ali, I think.
劳伦斯中尉 我想你见过阿里长官了
Yes, my lord.
是的，殿下
And now, Selim, "The Brightness."
这是赛林姆的“光明”
"By the noonday brightness...
“经由中午的光明”
...and by the night when it darkeneth...
“跟天黑后的夜晚”
...thy Lord hath not forsaken thee...
“真主是不会遗弃你的”
...neither hath He been displeased.
“祂也不会不悦”
And surely the future shall be better for thee than the past."
“你的未来当然比过去好”
"And in the end shall your Lord be bounteous to thee...
“在最后真主 将会慷慨地赐福于你”
...and thou be satisfied."
“而你将会满足”
So?
那么？
Yes, colonel.
是的，上校
- I want a decision, sir. - You want me to fall back on Yenbo.
- 我要你做决定，长官 - 你要我撤退回阳波
Well, you're not doing much good here, sir.
你在这里没有大用途
I'm sorry to rub it in, sir, but we can't supply you here.
我很抱歉这么说 但在这里我们不能为你提供补给
You could supply us through Aqaba!
你可以从阿卡巴来补给我们！
Aqaba!
阿卡巴！
If you can get ahold of Aqaba, we can supply you.
如果你守得住阿卡巴 我们就能给你补给
- But you can't! - You could.
- 但是你们不能！ - 你们可以的
You mean, the navy?
你是指海军吗？
The Turks have 12- inch guns at Aqaba, sir.
土耳其人在阿卡巴 部署了十二寸的机关枪
Can you imagine what that means?
你可以想像那是什么意思吗？
Yes, I can imagine.
对，我想像得到
Put that out of your mind, sir. The navy's got other things to do.
别想了，海军还有别的事要做
Oh, yes. Protecting the Suez Canal.
对，保护苏伊士运河
The one essential sector of this front is and must be the canal.
前线最重要的地方就是运河
You can see that, sir, surely.
你应该明白的
I see that the canal is an essential British interest.
我知道英国人对运河有兴趣
It is of little consequence to us.
那对我们来说没什么影响
I must ask you not to speak like that.
请你不要那么说
British and Arab interests are one and the same.
英国跟阿拉伯的目标是一样的
Possibly.
有可能
Upon my word, sir, you're ungrateful.
我得说，先生，你很不知感激
Fall back on Yenbo and we will give you equipment.
撤退回阳波 我们会补充设备给你的
Give you arms, advice, training, everything.
给你武器，建议，训练 什么都可以
- Guns? - A modern rifle for every man.
- 枪呢？ - 每个人都能有现代的来福枪
No. Guns. Artillery.
不，枪，大炮
Guns like the Turkish guns at Medina.
像是土耳其人在麦地纳用的枪
Yes, give us guns and keep the training.
对，给我们枪，不用训练我们
Your men need training far more than guns, sir.
你的手下 最需要的是训练而不是枪
English will teach Bedu to fight?
英国人要教 贝都因人如何战斗？
We will teach them, Sherif Ali, to fight a modern mechanized army.
阿里长官，我们会教他们 对抗一只现代化的机械式军队
Yes, lieutenant? What do you think about Yenbo?
是的，中尉？ 阳波的事你意见如何？
I think it is far from Damascus.
我觉得那里离大马士革很远
We'll have you in Damascus, sir. Never fear.
我们会把你送到大马士革的，别害怕
Have you been in Damascus, Mr. Lawrence?
你去过大马士革吗？劳伦斯先生
Yes, my lord.
去过，殿下
It is beautiful, is it not?
那里很漂亮，对吧？
- Very. - That will do, Lawrence.
- 非常漂亮 - 那就行了，劳伦斯
Dreaming won't get you to Damascus, but discipline will.
梦想不会带你去大马士革 但是自律可以
Look, Great Britain is a small country, much smaller than yours.
听着，英国是一个小国家 比你的国家还小
Small population compared with some.
跟某些国家相比人口很少
It's small, but it's great. And why?
它很小但很伟大，为什么？
- Because it has guns. - Because it has discipline.
- 因为它有枪 - 因为它有自律
Because it has a navy, because of this...
因为它有海军，所以…
...the English go where they please...
英国人想去哪里都行
...and strike where they please. This makes them great.
想攻击哪里都没问题 所以他们才会很伟大
- Right. - Mr. Lawrence, that will do!
- 对 - 劳伦斯先生，那样就行了
Lawrence is not your military adviser.
劳伦斯不是你的军事顾问
But I would like to hear his opinion.
但我想听听他的意见
Damn it! Who do you take your orders from?
该死！ 你听谁的命令呢？
From Lord Feisal, in Feisal's tent.
在费瑟的帐篷里 当然是费瑟殿下
Old fool! Why turn from him to him? They are master and man.
老笨蛋！为什么问完他后问他 他们一个是主人，一个是随从
My lord, I think...
殿下，我认为…
I think your book is right.
我认为你的书说的对
The desert is an ocean in which no oar is dipped.
沙漠是个没有船的海洋
On this ocean, the Bedu go where they please...
在这片海洋中贝都因人…
...and strike where they please.
想去哪里，想攻击那里都行
This is the way the Bedu has always fought.
贝都因人一直是这样作战的
You're famed through the world for fighting this way.
你因这个战法而名闻世界
And this is the way you should fight now.
你现在正需要这样打法
I don't know.
我不知道
I'm sorry, sir, but you're wrong.
抱歉，先生，你错了
Fall back on Yenbo, the Arab Rising becomes one unit in the British army.
撤退回阳波，阿拉伯提升组织 将成为英军的一个单位
- What is this to you? - You're a traitor.
- 对你来说这有什么好处？ - 你是个叛徒
No, colonel.
不，上校
He is a young man, and young men are passionate.
他是个年轻人，年轻人充满了热忱
They must say their say.
他们得说出想说的话
But wiser people must decide. I know you are right.
但聪明人得下决定 我知道你是对的
Very well. When shall we move? The sooner the better.
那么，我们何时走？越快越好
You'll lose another 50 men tonight.
你今晚会失去五十个手下
You tread heavily...
你的语气很强硬
...but you speak the truth.
但你说的话都是真的
I will give you my answer tomorrow. And now...
我明天会告诉你答案 但是现在…
...it is late.
已经很晚了
Colonel Brighton means to put my men...
布莱顿上校想把我的人…
...under European officers, does he not?
纳入欧洲军官麾下，对吧？
In effect, my lord, yes.
可以说，是的
And I must do it...
我必须这么做
...because the Turks have European guns.
因为土耳其人有欧洲人的枪
But I fear to do it...
但我害怕这么做
...upon my soul I do.
我以灵魂发誓，我真的怕
The English have a great hunger for desolate places.
英国人对荒凉之地比较有兴趣
I fear they hunger for Arabia.
我怕他们想拿下阿拉伯
Then you must deny it to them.
那你得挺身抵抗
You are an Englishman. Are you not loyal to England?
你是英国人，你不忠于英国吗？
To England and to other things.
我效忠于英国跟其他事情
To England and Arabia both?
你同时效忠于英国跟阿拉伯？
And is that possible?
那可能吗？
I think you are another of these desert- Ioving English.
我觉得你是 那种喜欢沙漠的英国人
Doughty, Stanhope...
多夫提，史丹霍普
...Gordon of Khartoum.
卡杜姆的葛登
No Arab loves the desert.
阿拉伯人不喜欢沙漠
We love water and green trees. There is nothing in the desert.
我们喜欢水跟绿树 在沙漠里什么都没有
And no man needs nothing.
人都是有需求的
Or is it that you think we are something you can play with...
或是你们觉得 我们是你们能玩弄的东西
...because we are a little people, a silly people...
因为我们是弱小愚蠢的民族
...greedy, barbarous and cruel?
贪婪，野蛮又残忍？
Or do you know, lieutenant, in the Arab city of Cordoba...
中尉，你知道 在阿拉伯的卡杜巴市…
...were two miles of lighting in the streets...
有两里长的街道设有路灯
...when London was a village.
当时伦敦还只是个小村子
Yes, you were great.
对，你们很伟大
Nine centuries ago.
那是九世纪前的事
Time to be great again, my lord.
该是你们恢复光荣的时候了，殿下
Which is why my father made this war upon the Turks.
所以我父亲 决定对土耳其人发动战争
My father, Mr. Lawrence, not the English.
劳伦斯先生，是我父亲 不是英国人
But my father is old...
但我父亲老了
...and I...
而我…
...I long for the vanished gardens of Cordoba.
我渴望着废弃的卡杜巴花园
However, before the gardens must come the fighting.
然而在得到花园前 得先经历苦战
To be great again, it seems that we need the English...
要再度恢复光荣 看起来我们需要英国人
...or...
或是…
Or?
或是？
What no man can provide, Mr. Lawrence.
没有人能提供的东西 劳伦斯先生
We need a miracle.
我们需要奇迹
Aqaba.
阿卡巴
From the land.
从陆地进攻
You are mad.
你疯了
To come to Aqaba by land we should have to cross the Nefud Desert.
经由陆路到阿卡巴 我们得越过尼法德沙漠
That's right.
没错
The Nefud cannot be crossed.
没人能越过尼法德沙漠
I'll cross it if you will.
如果你愿意的话，我可以穿越过它
You? It takes more than a compass, Englishman.
你？只靠罗盘是办不到的，英国人
The Nefud is the worst place God created.
尼法德沙漠是真主创造出来 最可怕的地方
I can't answer for the place. Only for myself.
我无法为地点做主 我只能为自己作主
Fifty men?
五十个士兵？
Fifty? Against Aqaba?
只靠五十个士兵拿下阿卡巴？
If 50 men came out of the Nefud...
如果这五十个人 能穿越尼法德沙漠
...they would be 50 men other men might join.
会有其他人 加入这五十个人的行列
The Howeitat are there, I hear.
听说霍威塔特人在那里
The Howeitat are brigands. They'll sell themselves to anyone.
霍威塔特人是土匪 他们愿意把自己出卖给任何人
- Good fighters, though. - Good...
- 但他们是好战士 - 没错
Yes. There are guns at Aqaba.
对，阿卡巴有枪炮
They face the sea, Sherif Ali, and cannot be turned around.
枪炮都面对大海，阿里长官 而且都无法转向
From the landward side, there are no guns at Aqaba.
就内陆这个方面来说 在阿卡巴没有枪
With good reason. It cannot be approached from the landward side.
是有理由的 我们无法从内陆接近阿卡巴
Certainly the Turks don't dream of it.
土耳其人绝对想像不到的
Aqaba's over there.
阿卡巴在那里
It's only a matter of going.
现在只要决定去
You are mad.
你疯了
And where are you going, lieutenant?
你要去哪里？中尉
With 50 of my men.
还带着我的五十个兄弟
To work your miracle.
去实现你的奇迹
Blasphemy is a bad beginning for such a journey.
咒骂神明不是旅程的好开始
- Who told you? - Ali did.
- 谁跟你说的？ - 阿里
Why not you?
为什么不是你呢？
You are falling back from Yenbo, sir?
你要从阳波撤退吗？
Yes, I must.
对，我必须撤退
But I will spare these to you.
但我会让你不必如此
Did Ali break confidence to tell me?
阿里是否违反誓言告诉我？
Sherif Ali owes you his allegiance, my lord.
阿里长官对你效忠，殿下
Yet you did not tell Colonel Brighton.
但你没告诉布莱顿上校
No.
对
Since you do know...
既然你知道…
...we can claim to arrive in the name of Feisal of Mecca.
我们可以以麦加费瑟之名展开远征
Yes, Lieutenant Lawrence, you may claim it.
对，劳伦斯中尉，你可以那么说
But in whose name do you ride?
但你要以谁之名展开远征呢？
Sherif, I caught them. They have tracked us.
长官，我抓到他们 他们一直在跟踪我们
They were here. I caught them.
他们来到这里，我抓到他们
Why are you here? Boy!
你们为什么要来这里？小子
To serve Lord Lawrence, sherif.
为了服侍劳伦斯大人，沙利夫
This is true, Lawrence. They do wish it.
真的，劳伦斯 他们真的希望那么做
You have been tracking us.
你们一直在跟踪我们
- You were told to stay. - No, sherif.
- 你奉命要留下来 - 不，沙利夫
Our camel strayed. We followed her.
我们的骆鸵迷路了 我们跟着他走
She led us here to be Lord Lawrence's servants.
他带我们来这里 当劳伦斯大人的随从
- It is the will of Allah. - Blasphemy.
- 这是阿拉的旨意 - 你们轻视神明
Don't do that.
别那么做！
No, Lawrence, these are not servants. These are outcasts, parent- less.
不，劳伦斯，这些人不是随从 他们是无父无母，被放逐的人
Be warned. They are not suitable.
我得警告你，他们并不适合
They sound very suitable. You can ride with the baggage.
他们听起来挺适合的 你们负责载运行李
These are not servants. These are worshippers.
他们不是随从，他们是朝圣者
One shilling, every week?
每星期一先令？
That is fair.
那很公平
- Each? - No.
- 每个人吗？ - 不
- That is too much. - All right.
- 那太多了 - 好吧
They will be lucky for you. Allah favours the compassionate.
能被你雇用是他们运气好 阿拉喜欢仁慈的人
There is the railway.
铁路在那边
And that is the desert.
那边是沙漠
From here until the other side, no water but what we carry.
从这里到另一边，没有水源 只有我们带来的水
For the camels, no water at all.
骆鸵根本没水喝
If the camels die...
如果骆鸵死了…
...we die.
我们就死定了
And in 20 days they will start to die.
在二十天后，他们会开始死亡
There's no time to waste, then, is there?
那么我们别浪费时间了，对吧？
I was thinking.
我在思考
You were drifting.
你在打瞌睡
Yes. It will not happen again.
对，以后不会再发生这种事了
Be warned, you were drifting.
小心，你在打瞌睡
It will not happen again.
以后不会再发生这种事了
That water is wasted.
那些水浪费了
From now on, we must travel by night...
从现在开始我们要在晚上出发
...and rest while it is too hot to travel.
热到不能行走时就休息
A few hours each day.
每天只能走几小时
Why don't we start now?
我们为什么不现在出发呢？
No. We will rest now.
不，我们现在休息
Three hours.
三小时
Fine.
好吧
I'll wake you.
我会叫你的
Do we rest here?
我们要在这里休息？
There is no rest now short of water.
没有水，现在别休息
The other side of that.
那儿的另一边
And how much of that is there?
那边有多少那儿呢？
I'm not sure.
我不确定
But however much, it must be crossed before tomorrow's sun gets up.
但不管有多少，我们得在 明天太阳升起前越过它
This is the sun's anvil.
这是个太阳的铁砧
Have we done it?
完成了吗？
No, but we're off the anvil.
还没，但我们逃过一劫
Thank God for that anyway.
谢天谢地
Yes, thank Him.
对，谢天谢地
Lawrence, I do not think you know how you have tempted Him.
劳伦斯，我想你不知道 你是怎么唆使祂的
I know.
我知道
We've done it.
我们完成了
God willing.
上天保佑
When do we reach the wells?
我们何时能到达水井？
God willing, midday.
上天保佑，中午
- Then we've done it. - Thank Him, Lawrence. Thank Him.
- 那么我们成功了 - 感谢上天吧，劳伦斯
Gasim's.
是嘉西姆的
What's happened to him?
他怎么了？
God knows.
天知道
Why don't you stop?
你为什么不停下来？
For what? He will be dead by midday.
为什么？他中午就会死的
We must go back.
我们得回去
What for, to die with Gasim?
为什么？为了跟嘉西姆一起死吗？
In one hour comes the sun.
一小时内太阳会升起
In God's name, understand! We cannot go back!
以上天为名，听清楚！ 我们不能回头！
I can.
我可以
Take the boys.
把那些男孩带着
If you go back, you kill yourself, is all.
如果你回头，你会害自己没命的
Gasim you have killed already.
你已经杀了嘉西姆
Get out of my way.
滚开
Gasim's time is come, Lawrence. It is written.
嘉西姆的时间到了，劳伦斯 那是注定的
Nothing is written!
没有什么事是注定的！
Go back, then!
那么掉头吧！
What did you bring us here for with your blasphemous conceit?
你为什么凭着你咒神又自大地 带着我们来到此地？
English blasphemer!
咒神的英国人！
Aqaba?
阿卡巴？
Was it Aqaba?
那是阿卡巴吗？
You will not be at Aqaba, English!
你到不了阿卡巴的，英国人！
Go back, blasphemer...
掉头吧，咒神狂
...but you will not be at Aqaba.
但你到不了阿卡巴的！
I shall be at Aqaba.
我会去阿卡巴的
That is written.
那是注定的…
In here.
在这里
English!
英国人！
Lawrence! Daud!
劳伦斯！杜德！
Nothing is written.
没有什么事是注定的
Al Lawrence.
艾尔劳伦斯
Farraj.
法拉吉
Wash.
洗一洗
Al Lawrence.
艾尔劳伦斯
Truly, for some men nothing is written unless they write it.
真的，那些不相信命运的人 总是要眼见为凭
Not Al Lawrence. Just Lawrence.
不是艾尔劳伦斯 只是劳伦斯
- AI Lawrence is better. - True.
- 艾尔劳伦斯比较好 - 没错
Your father too, just Mr. Lawrence?
你爸爸也一样吗？ 只是劳伦斯先生
My father is Sir Thomas Chapman.
我父亲是汤犸斯查普曼爵士
- Is that a lord? - A kind of lord.
- 他是个贵族吗？ - 算是吧
Then when he dies, you too will be a lord.
当他死了之后，你会继承他的地位
No.
不
You have an elder brother.
你有哥哥
But then, I do not understand this. Your father's name is Chapman.
但我不明白，你父亲姓查普曼
He didn't marry my mother.
他没娶我母亲
I see.
我懂了
I'm sorry.
抱歉
It seems to me that you are free to choose your own name, then.
那么我想你可以 自由地选择你的姓氏
Yes, I suppose I am.
对，我想是的
Al Lawrence is best.
艾尔劳伦斯是最棒的
All right, I'll settle for Al Lawrence.
好吧，那就叫艾尔劳伦斯吧
They are the robes of a sherif of the Beni Wejh.
这是班尼威哈长官的袍子
Very fine.
非常好
- Great honour. - The honour is to us. Salaam, sherif.
- 我很荣幸 - 我们也很荣幸，您好，长官
- Is it permitted? - Surely.
- 可以这样吗？ - 当然
He for whom nothing is written may write himself a clan.
没有注定姓氏的人可以 自由地注定你的家族
They are good for riding. Try.
穿了袍子骑骆鸵很方便，试试看
What are you doing, Englishman?
你在做什么？英国人
As you see.
你都看到了
Are you alone?
你一个人吗？
Almost.
差不多吧
Are you with those dogs drinking at my well?
你跟那些从我井里 取水喝的狗在一起吗？
Yours?
那是你的井？
I am Auda Abu Tayi.
我是奥达阿布塔耶
I've heard of another man of that name.
我听说过另一个跟你同名的人
Other? What other?
另一个人？什么另一个人？
The Auda I'd heard of wouldn't need to summon help to look after his wells.
我听说过的那个奥达 不需要别人帮忙保护他的水井
He must be a great hero.
他一定是个大英雄
He is.
是的
He wouldn't refuse water to men coming out of Nefud Desert.
他不会拒绝提供水 给从尼法德沙漠走出来的人
Now, would he not?
是吗？
No, that must be some other man.
对，所以他一定是另一个人
Here is my help.
我的助手来了
Son, what fashion is this?
孩子，这是什么服装？
- Harith, Father. - What manner of Harith?
- 这是哈利斯的服装 - 哈利斯的什么部族？
A Beni Wejh sherif.
这是班尼威哈长官的袍子
And is he Harith?
他是哈利斯人吗？
No, Father, English.
不，他是英国人
Son...
孩子
...they are stealing our water.
他们在偷我们的水
Tell them we are coming.
告诉他们我们来了
Tell them.
告诉他们
- Empty that! - Do not!
- 倒光它！ - 不要！
It is Auda of the Howeitat who speaks.
我是哈威塔特的奥达
It is Ali of the Harith who answers.
我是哈利斯的阿里
Harith.
哈利斯
Ali.
阿里
Does your father still steal?
你父亲还在偷东西吗？
No.
没有了
Does Auda take me for one of his own bastards?
奥达把我误认为 他自己的私生子吗？
No. There is no resemblance.
不，根本一点都不像
Alas, you resemble your father.
该死，你长得真像你父亲
- Auda flatters me. - You are easily flattered.
- 奥达是在奉承我 - 你很容易就被奉承了
I knew your father well.
我跟你父亲很熟
Did you know your own?
你认识你父亲吗？
We are 50, you are two. How if we shot you down?
我们有五十个人，你们只有两个 我们开枪射杀你们如何？
Why, then you have a blood feud with the Howeitat.
那么哈威塔特人会跟你们结下梁子
- Do you desire it? - Not the generals in Cairo...
- 你希望那样吗？ - 在开罗的将军…
...nor the sultan himself desire that.
跟土耳其国王都不希望这样
Call off your men.
叫你的人退下
This honours the unworthy.
这光荣是属于无价值的
I've only just begun to teach him.
我才刚开始教他
And what are you teaching him today? Howeitat hospitality?
你今天教了他什么？ 哈威塔特人的待客之道？
Be not clever with me, English.
别耍嘴皮子，英国人
- Who is he? - A friend of Prince Feisal's.
- 他是谁？ - 他是费瑟王子的朋友
- So you desire my hospitality? - Yes.
- 你希望我殷勤款待你？ - 对
Is he your tongue?
他是你舌头吗？
We do desire it.
我们真的很希望
Then it is given, if you will take it.
如果你要的话，我会答应你的
I'm at my summer camp, a poor place.
我在我的夏日别墅 那是个简陋的地方
Well, to me it seems a poor place. Some men find it marvellous.
对我来说那是个简陋的地方 有些人觉得那里很棒
Tomorrow, maybe I will allow the Turks to buy you, friends of Feisal.
明天或许我会准土耳其人买下你 费瑟的朋友
But...
但是…
...dine with me.
跟我共进晚餐吧
Dine with Auda, English.
跟奥达一起用餐，英国人
Dine with the Howeitat, Harith.
跟哈威塔特人一起用餐 哈利斯人
It is my pleasure that you dine with me in Wadi Rumm!
我很荣幸能跟你 一起在万迪拉姆用餐！
This thing you work against Aqaba...
你要进攻阿卡巴的事…
...what profit do you hope from it?
你希望得到什么好处呢？
We work it for Feisal of Mecca.
我们是为了麦加的费瑟才这么做的
The Harith do not work for profit.
哈利斯人做事不是为了求好处
Well, if it is in a man to be a servant, Sherif Ali...
如果有人一定要当仆人的话 阿里长官…
...he could find worse masters than Feisal.
也算是个好主人
But I... I cannot serve.
但我不能那么做
You permit the Turks to stay in Aqaba.
你允许土耳其人待在阿卡巴
Yes, it is my pleasure.
对，那是我的荣幸
We do not work this thing for Feisal.
我们这么做不是为了费瑟
No?
是吗？
- For the English, then? - For the Arabs.
- 那么是为了英国人？ - 是为了阿拉伯人
The Arabs?
阿拉伯人？
The Howeitat, Ageyil, Ruala, Beni Sahkr, these I know.
哈威塔特，阿吉亚尔，鲁阿拉 班尼夏卡尔，我知道这些部族
I have even heard of the Harith.
我听说过哈利斯人
But the Arabs?
但是阿拉伯人？
What tribe is that?
那是什么部族？
They're a tribe of slaves. They serve the Turks.
他们是奴隶 他们服侍土耳其人
Well, they are nothing to me.
他们对我来说什么都不是
My tribe is the Howeitat.
我是哈威塔特人
Who work only for profit.
做事只求好处
Who work at Auda's pleasure.
我们做事只为了取悦奥达
And Auda's pleasure is to serve the Turks.
而奥达的乐趣在于服侍土耳其人
Serve?
服侍？
I serve?
我会服侍人？
It is the servant who takes money.
拿钱的人是仆人
I am Auda Abu Tayi.
我是奥达阿布塔耶
- Does Auda serve? - No!
- 奥达会服侍人吗？ - 不
- Does Auda Abu Tayi serve? - No!
I carry 23 great wounds, all got in battle.
我身上的二十三处伤痕 都是在战争中受的伤
75 men have I killed with my own hands, in battle.
我在战争中亲手杀了七十五个人
I scatter, I burn my enemies tents. I take away their flocks and herds.
我屠杀燃烧敌人的帐篷 我夺走他们的族人跟牲畜
The Turks pay me a golden treasure, yet I am poor!
土耳其人付我金子 但我还是很穷！
Because I am a river to my people.
因为我是人民的河流
Is that service?
那是服侍吗？
No.
不是
And yet now it seems Auda has grown old.
看来奥达老了
And lost his taste for fighting.
失去了他的战斗力
It is well you say it in my tent, thou old tulip.
你敢在我的帐篷里这么说 真是大胆
Yet this is a tulip that the Turks could not buy.
这个胆大的人 是土耳其人收买不了的
Why should they wish to?
他们为什么要收买他？
Now...
好了
I will tell you what they pay me, and you will tell me if this is...
我告诉你他们给我什么 你告诉我这是否是…
...a servant's wages.
仆人的薪水
They pay me, month by month...
他们每个月付我…
...100 golden guineas.
一百个金币
150, Auda.
是一百五十个，奥达
- Who told you that? - I have long ears.
- 是谁告诉你的？ - 我的耳朵挺尖的
And a long tongue between them.
你的舌头也很长
100, 150, what matters? It's a trifle.
一百跟一百五十有什么差别？ 那只不过是一点钱
A trifle which they take from a great box they have.
他们是从一个大箱子 拿出这么一点钱来的
In Aqaba.
在阿卡巴
- In Aqaba? - Where else?
- 在阿卡巴 - 不然还有哪里？
You trouble me like women.
你像女人一样令我烦心
Friends, we've been foolish. Auda will not come to Aqaba.
朋友，我们太愚蠢了 奥达不会去的
- For money? - No.
- 为了钱？ - 不
- For Feisal? - No!
- 为了费瑟？ - 不
Nor to drive away the Turks.
也不是为了赶走土耳其人
He will come...
他会去…
...because it is his pleasure.
因为那是他的荣幸
Thy mother mated with a scorpion.
你妈跟蝎子上床
Make God your agent!
愿老天爷领导你们！
Aqaba!
阿卡巴！
God be with you.
愿真主与你同在
Yes.
对
Aqaba.
阿卡巴
Tomorrow we will go and get it.
明天我们会拿下它
- Do you think we shall? - Yes.
- 你觉得我们会成功吗？ - 会
If you are right about the guns.
如果枪炮的事你没说错
He killed. He dies.
他杀人，他得死
This is the end of Aqaba.
阿卡巴的事到此结束
One of our men murdered Auda's man.
我们的人杀了奥达的手下
Why?
为什么？
Theft? Blood feud? It makes no matter why.
小偷？世仇？为什么并不重要
Ali!
阿里！
It is an ancient wound.
那是道旧伤口
I didn't come here to watch a tribal bloodbath.
我不是来这里看部族血战的
It is the law, Lawrence.
这是法律，劳伦斯
The law says the man must die.
法律说这个人得死
If he dies, will that content the Howeitat?
如果他死了 哈威塔特人就满意了？
Yes.
对
Sherif Ali!
阿里长官！
If none of Lord Auda's men harms any of yours...
如果奥达大人的手下 不伤害你们…
...will that content the Harith? - Yes.
- 那么哈利斯人会满足吗？ - 对
Then I will execute the law.
那么我要执行法律
I have no tribe.
我没有部族
And no one is offended.
没人犯法
Gasim.
嘉西姆
Did you do it?
那是你做的吗？
Well, Lawrence...
劳伦斯
What ails the Englishman?
英国人在烦恼什么？
That that he killed was the man he brought out of the Nefud.
他杀的那个人是 他从尼法德沙漠救回来的
It was written, then.
那么那是注定好的
Better to have left him.
早知不去救他
It was execution, Lawrence. No shame in that.
这是在行刑，劳伦斯 没有什么可耻的
Besides, it was necessary.
而且这是必要的
You gave life and you took it.
你让他生，又让他死
The writing is still yours.
还是由你注定
Auda Abu Tayi!
奥达阿布塔耶！
The miracle is accomplished.
奇迹发生了
Garlands for the conqueror.
征服者的光荣
Tribute for the prince. Flowers for the man.
给王子的贡品，给英雄的花
I'm none of those things, Ali.
我什么都不是，阿里
- What, then? - Don't know.
- 那么你是什么？ - 我不知道
Thanks.
谢谢
My God, I love this country.
天啊，我爱这个国家
What!
什么！
No gold in Aqaba!
阿卡巴里没黄金！
Auda, I found it!
奥达，我找到了！
That's a pity.
那真的是太可惜了
Ali, get a message down the coast to Yenbo.
阿里，把消息传到阳波的海边去
Tell Feisal to find boats, any boats...
告诉费瑟找船，什么船都行
...and bring the Arab army here to Aqaba, quickly.
尽快把阿拉伯军队带到阿卡巴来
And you?
你呢？
I'm going to tell the generals...
我要去告诉…
...in Cairo.
在开罗的将军们
Yes, cross Sinai.
对，穿过西奈半岛
Come on!
来吧！
Sinai?
西奈半岛？
Yes.
对
- With these? - They'll be all right with me.
- 跟这些人？ - 他们跟我在一起没事的
Look, Ali. If any of your Bedouin arrived in Cairo and said:
听着，阿里 如果你的贝都因人跑到开罗说：
"We've taken Aqaba," the generals would laugh.
“我们拿下阿卡巴了” 将军们会一笑置之
I see.
我懂了
In Cairo you will put off these funny clothes.
在开罗，你得脱下那些可笑的衣服
You'll wear trousers and tell stories of our quaintness and barbarity...
你要穿上裤子 跟人们诉说我们的古怪跟野蛮
...and then they will believe you.
然后他们会相信你
You're an ignorant man.
你是个愚昧的人
Paper.
纸张
Paper!
纸张！
There is no gold in Aqaba.
阿卡巴没有黄金
No gold.
没有黄金
No great box!
没有大箱子！
Did Auda come to Aqaba for gold?
奥达来到阿卡巴是为了黄金吗？
For my pleasure, as you said.
就像你说过的，我是为了荣幸
But gold is honorable...
但黄金是荣耀的东西
...and Lawrence promised gold.
而劳伦斯答应会有黄金的
Lawrence lied.
劳伦斯说谎
See, Auda.
看好，奥达
"The Crown of England...
“英国的皇室”
...promises to pay...
“答应要付”
...5000 golden guineas...
“五千个金币”
...to Auda Abu Tayi."
“给奥达阿布塔耶”
Signed in His Majesty's absence...
“以国王殿下之名”
...by...
“我在此”
...me.
“签名”
In 10 days...
十天内…
...I'll be back with the gold.
我会带着黄金回来
With gold, with guns, with everything.
我会带枪，黄金跟所有的东西回来
Ten days.
十天
You'll cross Sinai?
你要穿过西奈半岛？
Why not?
为什么不行？
Moses did.
摩西曾那么做过
And you will take the children?
你要带着孩子们同行？
Moses did.
摩西曾那么做过
Moses was a prophet...
摩西是个圣徒
...and beloved of God.
他受上帝的垂爱！
He said there was gold here. He lied.
他说过这里有黄金，他骗人
He is not perfect.
他不完美
Lord, can we not rest?
天啊，我们能不休息吗？
I told you, no rest till they know that I have Aqaba.
我说过除非他们知道 我拿下阿卡巴，不然不能休息
Have you two slept in beds?
你们两个试过在床上睡吗？
Farraj?
法拉吉？
Daud?
杜德？
With sheets?
有床单的？
Tomorrow the finest sheets in the finest room and hotel in Cairo.
明天我们会在开罗最好的饭店里 最好的房间盖着最好的床单
I promise.
我保证
Then it shall be so, lord.
那么就这么说定了，大人
Look!
你看！
Pillar of fire.
是火柱
No, lord. Dust.
不，大人，是灰尘
My compass.
我的罗盘
No matter.
没关系
If we ride west, we must strike the canal.
如果我们往西走 一定可以走到运河那边
Due west.
往西前进
Come on!
来吧！
Lawrence!
劳伦斯！
Farraj!
法拉吉
Farraj, don't! Don't!
法拉吉，不要！…
Don't!
不要！
Why do you walk?
你为什么要走？
But why, lord?
为什么？大人
There is room for both. It serves no purpose.
这可以乘坐两个人，走路没意思
Lawrence, look!
劳伦斯，你看！
(警告)
It's all right, Farraj.
没关系的，法拉吉
It's all right.
没关系的
Who are you?
你是谁？
- Daud! - We're here, sir.
- 杜德！ - 我们在这里，大人
You taking him in there?
是你带他来的吗？
Yes.
是的
Here!
过来！
Here. You!
你给我过来！
And where the hell do you think you're going to, Mustapha?
你想去哪里啊？穆斯塔法
We are thirsty.
我们渴了
- Mr. Lawrence, is it? - Yes.
- 劳伦斯先生，是吗？ - 对
- Are you going to the officers' bar? - Yes.
- 你要去军官酒吧？ - 对
You can't take him in there, sir.
你不能带他进去，先生
What do you think you look like?
你觉得你像什么东西？
No, no. You must go.
不，你得离开
No, no. Go, effendi, go!
不，来吧，朋友！
Get out! You must get out! Get out!
滚出去！你得滚出去！滚出去！
We want two large glasses of lemonade.
我们要两杯大杯的柠檬汁
- This is a bar for British officers. - We are not particular.
- 这是英国军官的酒吧 - 我们并不介意
- Are you off your head? - No. Oddly enough I'm not.
- 你疯了吗？ - 不，很奇怪地我没疯
- Just clear out of here, will you? - Get that boy out of here.
- 请你快离开，好吗？ - 让那孩子滚出去
Corporal, we'll have this one out anyway.
下士，我们要把这家伙赶出去
- Get that wog out of here. - Clear off.
- 把那个混蛋赶出去 - 滚开
What's going on?
发生了什么事？
- It's Lawrence, sir. - Lemonade with ice.
- 是劳伦斯，长官 - 我要加冰的柠檬汁
Explain yourself.
你解释吧
We've taken Aqaba.
我们拿下阿卡巴了
- Taken Aqaba? Who has? - We have.
- 拿下阿卡巴？谁啊？ - 我们
Our side in this war has. The wogs have.
我们的战友拿下阿卡巴 那些混蛋成功了
We have.
我们成功了
He likes your lemonade.
他喜欢你的柠檬汁
You mean the Turks have gone?
你是说土耳其人离开了？
No, they're still there but they've no boots.
不，他们还在那儿 但是他们已经失势
Prisoners, sir. We took them prisoners. The entire garrison.
我们把他们全都关了起来 所有的部队都被关了起来
That's not true. We killed some.
那不是真的，我们杀了一些人
Too many, really. I'll manage it better next time.
事实上是很多人 我下次会处理的更好
There's been a lot of killing one way or another.
不论如何都会死很多人
Cross my heart and hope to die, it's all perfectly true.
我发毒誓，那是真的
- It isn't possible. - Yes, it is.
- 那是不可能的 - 那是真的
I did it.
我做到了
You'd better talk to Allenby.
你最好去跟艾伦比谈谈
- General Allenby? - He's in command. Murray's gone.
- 艾伦比将军？ - 现在他是指挥官，墨瑞走了
That's a step in the right direction.
那么做是对的
First I want a room. With a bed, with sheets.
首先我要一个房间，要有床跟床单
- Yes, of course. - It's for him.
- 对，当然 - 那是给他的
Right. You want a bed yourself, don't you?
对，你要一张自己的床，对吧？
See Allenby first, though.
但先去见艾伦比吧
Will he see me?
他会见我吗？
I think so.
我想会的
Do that, then.
那么就去做吧
- I'd better shave. - Yes, you had.
- 我最好去刮个胡子 - 对，没错
You'd better get into some trousers too.
你最好去换条裤子
"Undisciplined.
不自律
Unpunctual.
不守时
Untidy.
不整洁
Several languages.
数种语言
Knowledge of music...
音乐
...literature.
文学的知识
Knowledge of...
知识…
Knowledge of..."
You're an interesting man, there's no doubt about it.
毫无疑问地你是个有趣的人
- Who told you to take Aqaba? - Nobody.
- 谁要你拿下阿卡巴 - 没有人
- Sir. - Sir.
- 长官 - 长官
Then why did you?
那么你为什么要那么做？
- Aqaba's important. - Why is it important?
- 阿卡巴很重要 - 为什么它很重要？
- It's the Turkish route to the canal. - Not anymore.
- 那是土耳其人到运河的路线 - 不再是了
- They're coming through Beersheba. - I know, but we've gone to Gaza.
- 他们现在从比尔沙巴走 - 我知道，但我们进入了加萨
- So? - So that left Aqaba behind your right.
- 所以呢？ - 拿下阿卡巴对你来说很重要
True.
真的
And it will be further behind your right when you go for Jerusalem.
当你到耶路撒冷时 阿卡巴对你来说就更重要了
Am I going for Jerusalem?
我要到耶路撒冷去？
Yes.
对
Very well.
非常好
Aqaba behind my right.
阿卡巴对我来说很重要
It threatened EI' Arish and Gaza.
它能威胁艾尔阿瑞许跟加萨
Anything else?
还有别的吗？
Yes.
有
Aqaba's linked with Medina.
阿卡巴跟麦地纳相连
Do you think we should shift them out of Medina now?
你觉得我们现在 要把他们赶出麦地纳吗？
No. I think you should leave them there.
不，我想你们 应该把他们留在那里
You acted without orders, you know.
你在没接到 命令的情况下擅自行动
Shouldn't officers use their initiative at all times?
军官不是随时 都该主动进取吗？
Not really. It's awfully dangerous.
事实上不然，那太危险了
Yes, I know.
对，我知道
Already?
你已经知道了？
Yes.
对
I'm promoting you major.
我要把你升上少校
I don't think that's a very good idea.
我不觉得那是个好主意
I didn't ask you. I want you to go back...
我没问你意见，我要你回去…
...and carry on the good work.
继续执行你的成果
No. Thank you, sir.
不，谢谢您，长官
- Why not? - Well, I, it's...
- 为什么不？ - 我，那个…
Let me see now...
我想想看…
I killed two people. I mean, two Arabs.
我杀了两个人，我是说阿拉伯人
One was a boy.
其中一个是个孩子
That was...
那是…
...yesterday.
昨天的事
I led him into a quicksand.
我把他领进流沙里
The other was a man.
另一个是个男人
That was...
那是在…
...before Aqaba, anyway.
我们拿下阿卡巴之前的事
I had to execute him with my pistol.
我得用我的枪来处决他
There was something about it I didn't like.
我不喜欢这样的事
- Well, naturally. - No. Something else.
- 当然 - 不，还有别的事
That's all right. Let it be a warning.
没关系，把它当成是个警告吧
No. Something else.
不，还有别的事
What, then?
什么事？
I enjoyed it.
我喜欢那样
Rubbish. Rubbish and nerves. You're tired.
胡说八道，你疯了，你太累了
What do you mean coming dressed like that? Amateur theatricals?
你打扮成那样是什么意思？ 你现在是业余演员？
Yes. Entirely.
对，没错
Let me see that hat thing or whatever it is.
让我看看那个像帽子的东西
Fascinating gear they wear.
他们的装备很棒
How would I look in this, Harry?
我穿起来怎么样？哈利
- Damn ridiculous, sir. - Here, you keep it.
- 很可笑，长官 - 拿去，你留着吧
What I'm trying to say is I don't think I'm fit for it.
我想说的是我并不适合
Really? What do you think, Dryden?
真的吗？你觉得呢？戴丹
Before he did it, sir, I'd have said it couldn't be done.
在他那么做之前，长官 我会说那是不可能的
- Brighton? - I know what he thinks.
- 布莱顿？ - 我知道他的想法
I think you should recommend a decoration, sir.
我想你该进行授勋典礼
I don't think it matters what his motives were.
我觉得他的动机不重要
It was a brilliant bit of soldiering.
他指挥军队很出色
- Mr. Perkins! - Sir!
- 柏金斯先生！ - 长官！
Let's have a drink, gentlemen.
我们去喝一杯吧，男士们
- You've heard about this, Mr. Perkins? - Yes, sir.
- 你听说了吗？柏金斯先生 - 我听说了
- What do you think about it? - Bloody marvellous, sir. Well done.
- 你觉得如何？ - 真的是太棒，长官，做得好
- Thank you, Mr. Perkins. - Sir!
- 谢谢你，柏金斯先生 - 长官
Come on, then.
那么来吧
You're a clever man, sir.
你是个聪明人
No, but I know a good thing when I see one.
不，我懂得把握机会
That's fair, surely?
那很公平，对吧？
If I need a breakthrough to Jerusalem, I must concentrate, not dissipate.
若我得在耶路撒冷那边有突破 我得集中力量，不是消散力量
- Bravo. - You know better?
- 太棒了 - 你懂吗？
I fight like Clausewitz, then you fight like Saxe.
我跟克劳西威兹般作战 然后你像萨克森一样作战
We should do very well indeed, shouldn't we?
我们可以做得很好，对吧？
Easy, gentlemen, please.
男士们，轻松点
- Give us something to drink. - Of course, sir.
- 麻烦你端杯酒来 - 没问题
I'm here at the invitation of Major Lawrence.
我是受劳伦斯少校之邀前来的
Tracy.
崔西
Shall we go outside?
我们要到外面去吗？
So you hold bound the Turkish desert army?
你牵制住土耳其的沙漠军队了？
Yes.
对
With 1000 Arabs?
用一千个阿拉伯人？
1000 Arabs means 1000 knives.
一千个阿拉伯人 代表一千把刀子
Delivered anywhere, day or night.
不论日夜他们随时待命
It means 1000 camels.
代表着一千只骆鸵
That means 1000 packs of high explosives and 1000 crack rifles.
那代表一千包的炸药 跟一千把的来福枪
We can cross Arabia while Johnny Turk is still turning round.
当土耳其人还在团团转时 我们可以越过阿拉伯
I'll smash his railways.
我要粉碎他们的铁路
While he mends, I'll smash them somewhere else.
当他们忙着修护铁路时 我会在别地发动破坏行动
In 13 weeks I can have Arabia in chaos.
在十三个星期内 我可以让阿拉伯陷于混乱
You are going back, then?
那么你要回去啰？
Yes.
对
Of course I'm going back.
我当然要回去
Well, if we can see it, so can the Turk.
如果我们想得到 那么土耳其人也想得到
If he finds he's using four divisions to fend off a handful of bandits...
如果他们发现得用四个军队 来防守一小群的土匪…
...he'll withdraw.
他们会撤退的
He daren't withdraw. Arabia's part of his empire.
他们不敢撤退的 阿拉伯是他们帝国的一部份
If he gets out now, he'll never get back again.
如果他们现在离开 他们永远都无法回来了
- I wonder who will. - No one will.
- 不知道谁能拥有此地 - 没有人可以
Arabia's for the Arabs now.
阿拉伯现在是阿拉伯人的
That's what I've told them anyway.
反正我是那么告诉他们的
That's what they think.
他们是那么想的
- That's why they're fighting. - Oh, surely.
- 那就是他们战斗的原因 - 当然
They've only one suspicion.
他们只有一个怀疑
That we'll let them drive the Turks out and then move in ourselves.
我们让他们赶走土耳其人 然后自己占据了阿拉伯
I've told them that that's false, that we have no ambitions in Arabia.
我告诉他们那是不对的 我们对阿拉伯没兴趣
Have we?
是吗？
I'm not a politician, thank God.
谢天谢地，我不是政客
Have we any ambition in Arabia, Dryden?
我们对阿拉伯有兴趣吗？戴丹
Difficult question, sir.
这是个很难的问题
I want to know, sir, if I can tell them in your name...
我想知道能否以你之名告诉他们
...that we've no ambitions in Arabia.
我们对阿拉伯没兴趣
Certainly.
当然可以
2000 small arms, not enough. I need five.
两千件兵器还不够 我需要五千件
Right.
好
Money. It'll have to be sovereigns. They don't like paper.
还有钱，我要金币 他们不喜欢纸钞
- Instructors for the Lewis guns. - Right.
- 路易斯枪只的指导老师 - 好
More money.
更多的钱
- How much more? - 25,000 now. A lot more later.
- 更多是多少？ - 现在要两万五，日后要更多
- Dryden? - It can be done, sir.
- 戴丹？ - 没问题，长官
A couple of armoured cars.
几部武装车辆
Right.
好
Field artillery.
大炮
Right.
好
I'll give you every blessed thing I can...
我会尽力提供你需要的东西
...because I know you'll use it. Congratulations.
因为我知道你会用到它们，恭喜
Thank you for your hospitality, gentlemen.
谢谢你们的招待，绅士们
Congratulations!
恭喜！
Are you really going to give them artillery, sir?
你真的要给他们大炮吗？长官
I was wondering that, sir.
我很怀疑啊
Might be difficult to get it back.
要把它们拿回来可能很难
Give them artillery and you've made them independent.
给他们大炮，等于让他们独立
Then I can't give it to them, can I?
那就不能给他们大炮，对吧？
- For you to say. - No, it's not.
- 那是你的决定 - 不是
I've got orders to obey, thank God.
我得遵守命令，谢天谢地
Not like that poor devil.
跟那个可怜的家伙不同
He's riding the whirlwind.
他像是在骑着旋风
Let's hope we're not.
希望我们不是
(休息时间)
Excuse me, friend. Who do these bags belong to?
对不起，朋友 这些袋子是什么人的？
To Prince Feisal.
是费瑟王子的
- You're not Prince Feisal? - No.
- 你不是费瑟王子吧？ - 我不是
You know him though?
你认识他吗？
He is my master. I am his servant.
他是我的主人，我是他的仆人
Can you read?
你识字吗？
(J.E.班特利先生)
Chicago Courier is my paper, but my work is syndicated in America.
我是芝加哥快报的记者 但我文章在美国多家报社刊登
I understood so from your letter, Mr. Bentley.
我从你的来信中知道了 班特利先生
Now...
好了
- Where can I find Major Lawrence? - Is that what you have come for?
- 我在哪里能找到劳伦斯少校？ - 那是你来此地的目的吗？
Not altogether, sir, no.
我不是只为了这件事而来
Well, Mr. Bentley, you will find Major Lawrence with my army.
班特利先生 劳伦斯少校在我的军队里
That's what I meant, sir. Where can I find your army?
那就是我的意思，先生 我在哪里能找到你的军队？
I don't know.
我不知道
- Last week they were near El Ghira. - Ghira?
- 上星期他们在艾尔盖拉附近 - 盖拉？
Yes, I fear you have a long journey. Can you ride a camel?
对，恐怕你得走上一段路 你会骑骆鸵吗？
- I've never tried. - Take a mule.
- 我从来都没试过 - 那你骑骡子吧
Avoid Mellaha, the Turks are there.
避开米拉哈，那里有土耳其人
In Mellaha now? They move fast.
他们现在在米拉哈？ 他们的动作真快
They do.
没错
But not so fast as we do, you will find.
但没我们快，你会看到的
Myself...
我自己…
...I am going to Cairo.
要到开罗去
- As you know. - Yes.
- 你是知道的 - 对
There's work for me there of a different kind.
那里有别的工作等着我去做
Yes.
对
I understand you've been given no artillery.
我知道你一直都没拿到大炮
- That is so. - You're handicapped?
- 没错 - 你陷入困境了？
It restricts us to small things.
这让我们被局限在小事上
It's intended to.
正是他们的计划
Do you know General Allenby?
你认识艾伦比将军吗？
Watch out for Allenby. He's a slim customer.
小心艾伦比 他是个狡猾的家伙
- Excuse me? - A clever man.
- 对不起 - 他是个聪明人
Slim customer. It's very good.
狡猾的家伙，说的好
I'll certainly watch out for him. You're being very sympathetic.
我当然会小心他 你真的是太好心了
Your Highness, we Americans were once a colonial people.
殿下，美国人也曾是殖民
We naturally feel sympathetic to any people...
我们当然会同情
...who struggle for their freedom.
那些为争取自由而努力的人
Very gratifying.
真的是太好了
Also, my interests are the same as yours. You want your story told.
还有我的目的跟你一样 你希望世人知道你的故事
I badly want a story to tell.
我很需要一个这样的故事
Ah, now you are talking turkey, are you not?
你在胡扯了，对吧？
I will give you a guide and a letter.
我会派响导给你 并帮你写一封信的
And before I leave here...
在我离开这里之前…
...which must be presently...
我得立刻离开
...I will have some facts and figures put on paper for you.
我会写下一些事实跟数字给你
You know that we are destroying the Turkish railways.
你知道我们在破坏土耳其人的铁路
I do, sir.
是的，殿下
Major Lawrence is in charge of all this, is he?
劳伦斯少校负责这次的行动，对吧？
My army is made up of tribes.
我的军队是由沙漠部族所组成的
The tribes are led by the tribal leaders.
部族是由族长所领导
Your people do think very highly of Major Lawrence?
你的人民很尊重劳伦斯少校吗？
Oh, yes. And the rightly.
没错，你说的对
In this country, Mr. Bentley...
班特利先生，在这个国家…
...the man who gives victory in battle is prized...
能够为战争带来胜利的人…
...beyond every other man.
能得到最高的尊敬
One figure I can give you from my head...
我现在就可以告诉你一个人…
...because it never leaves my head.
因为我从没忘记过
Since starting this campaign four months ago, we have lost...
自从四个月前开始这项行动后 我们有…
...37 wounded...
三十七人受伤…
...156 dead.
一百五十六人死亡
You remark the disproportion between our dead and wounded.
请注意死伤人数的比例不平衡
Yeah.
对
Four times as many.
死者比伤者多了四倍
That's because those too wounded to bring away, we ourselves kill.
那是因为 我们会杀了受伤太重的人
We leave no wounded for the Turks.
我们不会让伤者 落入土耳其人手中
- You mean...? - We leave no wounded for the Turks.
- 你是说…？ - 我们不会让伤者落入敌人手中
In their eyes, we are not soldiers but rebels.
在他们的眼中 我们不是士兵而是叛徒
Rebels, wounded or whole, are not protected by the Geneva Code...
叛徒不管是受伤还是健全 都不受日内瓦公约保护…
...and are treated harshly.
而且被敌人残忍地虐待着
How harshly?
有多残忍？
More harshly than I hope you can imagine.
那种情况是你想像不到的
I see.
我懂了
Our own prisoners are taken care of until the British...
我们的囚犯受到妥善照顾 直到我们…
...can relieve us of them, according to the Code.
根据公约把他们放给英国人
- I should like you to notice that. - Yes, sir.
- 我希望你能记住这一点 - 是的，先生
Is that the influence of Major Lawrence?
那是劳伦斯少校的影响吗？
Why should you suppose?
你为什么会那么想？
It's just that I heard in Cairo that...
只是我在开罗听说…
...Major Lawrence has a horror of bloodshed.
劳伦斯少校讨厌杀人
That is exactly so.
事实的确如此
With Major Lawrence, mercy is a passion.
对劳伦斯少校而言 仁慈是他所爱的
With me, it is merely good manners.
对我来说那只是一种好礼貌
You may judge which motive is the more reliable.
你可以判断 哪一项动机比较信得过
- And now, perhaps... - Oh, sure, sure.
- 好了，或许… - 当然
Thank you, sir.
谢谢您，先生
Can you manage the letter...?
你能把信写得…？
I'll do everything I have said...
我会实践我说过的话…
...if you will tell me truly the nature of your interest...
只要你诚实地告诉我 你为何对…
...in my people and Major Lawrence.
我的人民跟劳伦斯少校的事有兴趣
It's very simple, sir. I'm looking for a hero.
很简单，先生 我在寻找一个英雄
Indeed. You do not seem a romantic man.
没错，你看起来 不像是个浪漫的人
Oh, no.
对
But influential men back home believe it's time for America...
但我老家那些有影响力的人相信…
...to lend her weight to the struggle against Germany.
美国该挺身而出对抗德国
And Turkey.
跟土耳其
I've been sent to find material to show our people that this war is...
我来采访新闻 告诉我的国人这场战争…
- Enjoyable? - Hardly that, sir.
- 很好玩？ - 不是那样的，先生
But to show it in its more adventurous aspects.
是用更冒险的角度来报导它
You look for a figure who will draw your country towards war.
你在寻找一个能让 你的国家参战的人
All right. Yes.
好吧，对
Lawrence is your man.
劳伦斯是你要的人
Stop!
停火！
Stop it!
Come on, men!
快点，大伙们！
Lawrence!
劳伦斯！
Good God! God!
天啊！
Jiminy! Never seen a man killed with a sword before.
吉米尼！我从没看过 有人这样被剑杀死
Why don't you take a picture?
你为什么不照张相呢？
Wish I had.
我希望我照了
How is it with thee, Lawrence?
你好吗？劳伦斯
Am I in this?
我在里面吗？
Did you take his picture?
你有帮他拍照吗？
Yeah.
拍了
You are using up your nine lives very quickly.
很快地你的九条命都会没了
Charming company you keep.
你的同伴挺不错的
Auda?
奥达？
He's a bit old- fashioned. He thinks these things will steal his virtue.
他有点老古板，他觉得 这些东西会吸走他的灵魂
He thinks you're a kind of thief.
他觉得你是小偷
It's all right to take your picture?
可以替你拍张照吗？
- All right. - Okay.
- 好吧 - 好
Just walk.
走吧
Major Lawrence!
劳伦斯少校！
Yes, sir, that's my baby.
对，这才是我的宝贝
This looting has got to stop!
这种洗劫的行为得停止！
It is customary.
这是习俗
It's theft. And theft makes thieves.
这是偷窃，小偷才会偷东西
I would not say that to Auda.
我不会那么跟奥达说
- It is their payment, colonel. - Payment.
- 那是他们的薪水，上校 - 薪水
Truly. Are not British soldiers paid?
真的，英国士兵没有薪水吗？
- They don't go home when being paid. - They are not free to.
- 他们拿了薪水就不想回家 - 他们无法自由回家
Well, there's another lot you've seen the last of.
你再不会看到他们了
They'll come back.
他们会回来的
He says they'll come back. Will they?
他说他们会回来，会吗？
Not this year, Lawrence.
今年不会，劳伦斯
Look, Lawrence, how many men do you think you'll have left? 200?
听着，劳伦斯，你觉得你们 会剩下多少人？两百人吗？
- Less. - Well, then?
- 会更少 - 那么是多少？
I said, they'll come back.
我说过他们会回来的
You badly hurt?
你伤的很重吗？
Not hurt at all.
我根本没受伤
Didn't you know? They can only kill me with a golden bullet.
你不知道吗？ 他们只有用金子弹才杀得了我
(小市民，我们的国会)
It is for children. I have set myself to learn again.
这是给孩子的书 我得督促自己再学一次
- What are you learning from this? - Politics.
- 你从这件事里学到什么？ - 政治
You'll be a democracy in this country? You gonna have a parliament?
你会在本国行民主政治吗？ 你会成立国会吗？
I will tell you that when I have a country.
当我成立了国家 我再回答你这些问题
Did I answer well?
我回答得好吗？
You answered without saying anything. That's politics.
你回答了，但什么都没说 那就是政治
You learn quickly.
你学的很快
I have a good teacher.
我有一个好老师
Yeah.
对
- How's your hurt? - Fine.
- 你伤得如何？ - 我很好
Before I return to the fleshpots, which I shall be very glad to do...
在我回到战场前 而且我非常乐意那么做
...may I put two questions to you, straight?
我能直接地问你两个问题吗？
I'd be interested to hear you put a question straight.
我想听你直接地问一个问题
One.
一
What, in your opinion, do these people hope to gain from this war?
你觉得这些人希望从 这场战争里得到什么？
They hope to gain their freedom.
他们希望获得他们的自由
Freedom.
自由
"They hope to gain their freedom."
“他们希望获得他们的自由”
- There's one born every minute. - They're going to get it.
- 他们受骗了 - 他们会得到自由的
I'm going to give it to them.
我会让他们得到自由的
- The second question? - Well, I was going to ask...
- 第二个问题呢？ - 我要问的是…
...what is it that attracts you personally to the desert?
沙漠是什么地方吸引你呢？
It's clean.
它很干净
Well, now...
好了
...that's a very illuminating answer.
那是个很棒的答案
May I...
我可以…
...take one farewell picture?
拍一张告别照片吗？
I gave Math Budad two lamps for it.
我给麦斯巴德两个灯才换到它
One clock for two lamps.
一个钟换两个灯
A fair bargain.
一项很公平的交易
Fair? I robbed him.
公平？我是在抢劫他
Trash.
垃圾
I must find something honorable.
我得找到一些荣耀的东西
Honorable?
荣耀的东西？
The year is running out, Brighton.
今年快过完了，布莱顿
I must find something honorable.
我得找到一些荣耀的东西
Now you may blow up my train.
你现在可以炸了我的火车
And what will you do now?
你要做什么？
Now I go home. They will carry my toys.
我现在要回家 他们把我的玩具载走
They will carry my toys too, see?
他们也会载我的玩具 你懂吗？
Major Lawrence will campaign this winter.
劳伦斯少校 今年冬天会发动攻势
But you got what you wanted, so you're going home, is that it?
但你得到你想要的东西 所以要回家去，对吧？
Of course. When Lawrence has got what he wants, he will go home.
当然，当劳伦斯得到他 想要的东西，他会回家去的
When you've got what you want, you will go home.
当你得到你想要的东西时 你也会回家去的
No, I shan't, Auda.
不，我不会的，奥达
Then you are a fool.
那么你是个笨蛋
Maybe. But I am not a deserter.
或许吧，我不是个逃兵
Give thanks to God, Brighton...
谢天谢地，布莱顿
...that when He made you a fool, He gave you a fool's face.
当祂把你变成一个呆瓜时 祂也让你一脸的呆相
You are an impudent rascal.
你是个无礼的混蛋
I must go, Lawrence, before I soil myself with a fool's blood.
我得走了，劳伦斯 不然我也要成为笨蛋了
Like talking to a brick wall.
我像是在对牛弹琴
So what will you do now? What can you do?
你现在要做什么？ 你能做什么？
I'll go north.
我要往北走
That's what Allenby wants.
那就是艾伦比想要的
Allenby wanted the Arab army behind Deraa.
艾伦比要阿拉伯军队撤到迪拉之后
Then that's where I'll take it.
那么我会把他们领到那儿
Tell Allenby to hurry up, or we'll be in Deraa before he's in Jerusalem.
叫艾伦比快一点，不然在他 到耶路撒冷前我们就到迪拉了
Won't we?
对吧？
Train, Farraj.
火车，法拉吉
Yeah, Lawrence.
对，劳伦斯
Hide yourself, my friend.
躲起来，我的朋友
Detonator.
引爆器
All right, fetch another.
好了，再拿一个来
- Pardon, Lawrence. I put... - Plenty of time. Fetch another.
- 对不起，劳伦斯，我放… - 时间还很多，再拿一个来
Farraj?
法拉吉？
- What happened? - Detonator. A detonator!
- 发生什么事了？ - 引爆器！…
He cannot ride, Lawrence. Look.
他无法骑乘了
If they take him alive, you know what they'll do to him.
如果他们活抓他 你知道他们会如何折磨他的
Daud will be angry with you.
杜德会生你气的
Salute him for me.
帮我向他致意
What will you do now?
你现在要做什么？
Go north.
往北走
With twenty?
只带二十个人？
What would you recommend me to do?
你建议我该怎么做呢？
What would you recommend?
你会如何建议呢？
He hasn't 1 l10 so many men, sir.
他手下的人不到十分之一
He's lied, in fact.
事实上他在骗人
Yes and no. He doesn't claim to have done anything he hasn't done.
对也不对，他没说 他有做出他根本没做的事
Then there is an Arab north army.
那么就有一队阿拉伯北军啰
- No, sir, he has lied about that. - Any idea why?
- 不，长官，他在这一点说谎 - 你知道为什么吗？
- It's his army, I suppose. - It's Prince Feisal's army.
- 我想那是他的军队 - 那是费瑟王子的军队
Do you think he's gone native, Harry?
你觉得他会被同化吗？哈利
No.
不会的
He would if he could, I think.
我想如果可以的话，他会的
- Not my line of country. - It doesn't matter. Just curious.
- 就我对国家的观念不会的 - 这不重要，我只是好奇
What matters is I believed it.
重要的是我相信它
The Turks believe it.
土耳其人相信它
They are offering 20,000 pounds for him.
他们提供两万镑在悬赏他
Good heavens.
天啊
- Shouldn't say he had long to live. - Whatever else, he's a brave man...
- 看来他活不久了 - 他是个勇敢的人…
Surely, surely. If he's still going north with 50 men, he doesn't lack guts.
没错，如果他还敢带 五十个人北行，他的确很有种
I wonder if they'd offer that much for me.
不知道他们 会不会出这么多钱来悬赏我
What about next year? Will they still come back?
明年呢？他们还会回来吗？
I wouldn't be surprised.
我并不讶异
- They think he's a kind of prophet. - They do or he does?
- 他们觉得他是圣徒？ - 是他们或是他？
- Now may I speak? - Yes.
- 我可以说句话吗？ - 当然可以
One more failure and you will find yourself alone.
再失败一次 你会发现自己孤独一人
- I do not include myself. - I do not include the others.
- 不包括我 - 不包括其他人
So say they love you.
他们爱你
The more reason to be thrifty with them.
更应该对他们要求低些
Give them something to do that can be done. But you, no.
给他们做的好的任务 但你没那么做
They must move mountains, walk on water.
他们得移开高山 在水面上行走
That's right. That's right.
没错
Who are you to know what can be done?
你凭什么知道人能做什么事？
If we'd done what you thought could be done, we'd be in Yenbo now.
若我们完成你觉得可以 做到的事，我们早在阳波了
Whatever I ask them to do can be done. They know that if you don't.
我要他们做到的事都能做得到 你不明白，他们也明白
Do you think I'm just anybody?
你认为我只是一个普通人？
Do you?
是吗？
My friends, who will walk on water with me?
我的朋友谁要跟我走在水面上？
- Who will come with me into Deraa? - Deraa is garrisoned.
- 谁要跟我进入迪拉？ - 迪拉戒备森严
Will you take 20 against 2000?
你要以二十人攻打两千人？
- I'll go by myself if I have to. - Why?
- 如果有必要，我会自己去 - 为什么？
Because I told the English generals...
我告诉英国将军…
...the Arab revolt would be in Deraa when they'd be in Jerusalem.
当他们到耶路撒冷时 阿拉伯暴动会在迪拉
Or perhaps you are here...
或许你是为了英国的将军们…
...for the English generals.
来到这里
Who says this?
谁说的？
Rumour.
传言是如此
That is not an argument.
那不算是争论
Oh, argument.
争论
This afternoon I will take the Arab revolt into Deraa...
今天下午当阿拉伯人还在争论…
...while the Arabs argue.
我要带阿拉伯暴动进入迪拉
Can you pass for an Arab in an Arab town?
你能在阿拉伯的村落 假扮成阿拉伯人而不被认出吗？
Yes. If one of you would lend me some dirty clothes.
可以，如果你们愿意 借我一些脏衣服
It's madness.
那太疯狂了
What are you looking for?
你在找什么？
Some way to announce myself.
宣布我的到来的方法
Be patient with him, God.
对他有点耐心，天啊
- Do you not see how they look at you? - Peace, Ali, I am invisible.
- 你不知道他们怎么看你吗？ - 冷静，阿里，没人看得到我
Halt!
站住！
Walk on.
继续走
- Halt! - Walk on.
- 站住！ - 继续走
You and you.
你跟你
You.
你
You have blue eyes.
你的眼珠是蓝色的
- I say you have blue eyes. - Yes, effendi.
- 我说你的眼珠是蓝色的 - 对，朋友
- Are you Circassian? - Yes, effendi.
- 你是瑟卡新人吗？ - 对，朋友
How old are you?
你几岁？
Twenty- seven, effendi.
我二十七岁，朋友
I think.
我想
You look older. You have had a lot of experience.
你看起来比实际年龄老 你一定经历过很多事
It's an interesting face.
那是个长得很有趣的脸
I am surrounded by cattle.
我被牛包围着
He wouldn't know an interesting face from a sow's belly.
他根本连有趣的脸 是什么都不知道
I have been is Deraa now for three and a half years.
我到迪拉来三年半了
If they posted me to the dark side of the moon, I could not be more...
就是他们把我派到月球背面布岗 我也不会觉得…
...isolated.
孤单
You haven't the least idea what I'm talking about.
你不知道我在说什么
No, effendi.
对，朋友
Have you?
是吗？
No.
对
That would be too...
那真的是…
...lucky.
太幸运了
Where did you get that?
你打哪弄来这个？
- It's old, effendi. - No, this is recent.
- 这是旧伤了，朋友 - 不，这是新的
- You are a deserter. - No, effendi.
- 你是个逃兵 - 不是的，朋友
Yes, you are a deserter.
是，你是个逃兵
But from which army?
但是从哪个军队逃出来的呢？
Not that it matters at all.
那不重要
A man cannot be always in uniform.
人不可能老是穿制服
Your skin is very fair.
你的皮夫很漂亮
Beat him.
打他
To me!
给我！
Sleep.
睡吧
Eat.
吃
You have a body, like other men.
你有个跟其他男人一样的身体
Good.
很好
Then sleep.
那么睡吧
Better?
好一点了吗？
Much better. You were right.
好多了，你说的对
Rest, rest. Can you not learn?
休息吧，你学不乖吗？
Oh, I've learned all right.
我已经学到教训了
I'm going, Ali.
我要走了，阿里
- Why? - Why?
- 为什么？ - 为什么？
Heavens.
天啊
Why?
为什么？
I've come to the end of myself, I suppose.
我想我已经完了
And the end of the Arab revolt?
阿拉伯叛乱呢？
I'm not the Arab revolt, Ali. I'm not even Arab.
我不是阿拉伯叛乱，阿里 我甚至不是阿拉伯人
A man can be whatever he wants. You said.
你说人可以变成他想成为的人
I'm sorry. I thought it was true.
抱歉，我以为那是真的
You proved it.
你证明了这一点
Look, Ali. Look.
听着，阿里
That's me. What colour is it? That's me.
那是我，是什么颜色？ 那是我
And there's nothing I can do about it.
是我改不了的
A man can do whatever he wants. You said.
你说人可以变成他想成为的人
He can...
他可以…
...but he can't want what he wants.
但他不能随心所欲
This is the stuff that decides what he wants.
这是决定他要什么的东西
You may as well know. I would've told them anything.
你也知道吧 我想什么都告诉他们
I would've told them who I am. I would've told them where you were.
我想告诉他们我是谁 我想告诉他们你要去哪里
- I tried to. - So would any man.
- 我试着要说 - 任何人都会那么做的
Well, any man is what I am.
我只是个平凡人
And I'm going back to Allenby to ask him for a job...
我要回去跟艾伦比…
...that any man can do.
要一个平凡人的工作
Allenby's in Jerusalem.
艾伦比在耶路撒冷
- I'll make easy stages. - You?
- 我要做些轻松的事 - 你？
Oh, yes. Easy stages.
对，我要做些轻松的事
Look, Ali, I think I see a way of being just...
听着，阿里，我想我可以有…
...ordinarily...
一种平凡的…
...happy.
快乐
Can I take this?
我能拿走这个吗？
It is not clean.
它不干净喔
No, but it's warm.
对，但是很温暖
And these...
他们呢…
...having led them here, have you no care for them?
带领他们到这里来 你不在乎他们吗？
You lead them. They're yours. Trust your own people.
你带领他们，他们是你的了 相信你的人民
And let me go back to mine.
让我回到我的人民身边
- I say, don't forget those form fives. - All right.
- 别忘了那些五人小组 - 好吧
Mind if I join you?
介意我加入吗？
Honoured, sir.
这是我的荣幸
- Good to be back. - We heard you were, sir.
- 回来了真好 - 我们都听说你回来了，先生
- What's doing out there? - Where?
- 那边发生了什么事？ - 哪里？
- Arabia? - Well, yes, sir.
- 阿拉伯？ - 是的，先生
Nothing much. Wrong time of year. What's doing here?
没什么，现在是淡季 这里呢？
We're settling in. We built a squash court.
我们在安顿 我们盖了一座球场
Jolly good.
太好了
Well, I have to go up there.
我得上去了
It's borrowed. Someone pinched mine.
那是借来的 有人把我的偷走了
Bloody wogs.
真是混蛋
Yes, probably.
对啊，或许吧
Jolly good about the squash court.
球场那件事真是个好主意
Lays it on a bit thick, doesn't he?
他太夸张了，对吧？
Morning.
早安
- Good morning, sir. - Good to be back.
- 早安 - 回来了真好
- I'll believe you, sir. - No, really it is.
- 我相信你，先生 - 不，是真的
Hello.
嗨
Morning. You're to go right in.
早安，直走进去
Lawrence.
劳伦斯
Or is it Major Lawrence?
或我该叫你劳伦斯少校？
Sir.
长官
Well, general, I will leave you.
将军，我要离开了
Major Lawrence doubtless has reports to make...
劳伦斯少校毫无疑问地要报告…
...about my people and their weakness...
关于我的人民跟他们的弱点…
...and the need to keep them in the British interest.
及让英国对他们 保持利益权的必要
And the French interest too. We must not forget the French.
法国人也有利益权 我们别忘了法国人
I told you, sir, no such treaty exists.
我说过了并没有这样的条约限制
Yes, general, you have lied most bravely, but not convincingly.
对，将军，你很勇敢地说谎 但说服力却不够
I know this treaty does exist.
我知道的确有条约存在
Treaty, sir?
条约？
He does it better than you, general.
他的表演比你好，将军
But then, of course, he is almost an Arab.
当然他可以说是个阿拉伯人
You really don't know?
你真的不知道吗？
Then what the devil's this?
那么这到底是怎么一回事？
It's my request for release from Arabia, sir.
是我要求调离阿拉伯的申请信 先生
For what reason?
为什么？
You sure you haven't heard of the Sykes- Picot Treaty?
你确定你没听说过 史凯奇皮哥特条约？
No.
我没听过
- I can guess. - Don't guess. Tell him.
- 我猜想得到 - 别猜了，告诉他吧
Well, now...
好了
Mr. Sykes is an English civil servant.
史凯奇先生是一名英国公仆
Monsieur Picot is a French civil servant.
皮哥特先生是一名法国公仆
Mr. Sykes and Monsieur Picot met, and they agreed that after the war...
史凯奇跟皮哥特见面 他们同意在战后…
...France and England should share the Turkish Empire.
英法该共享土耳其帝国
Including Arabia.
包括阿拉伯在内
They signed an agreement, not a treaty, sir.
他们签订同意书而不是和约
An agreement to that effect.
同意书是有法律效力的
There may be honour among thieves, but there's none in politicians.
小偷之间或许还有尊严 但政客是无耻的
And let's have no displays of indignation.
我们别生气
You may not have known, but you certainly had suspicions.
你也许还不知道 但你有怀疑
If we've told lies, you've told half- lies.
如果我们是在说谎 你有一半也是在说谎
And a man who tells lies, like me, merely hides the truth.
像我这样说谎的人 只是在隐瞒事实
But a man who tells half- lies has forgotten where he put it.
但说一半谎话的人 忘了事实是什么
The truth is I'm an ordinary man.
真相是我是个普通人
You might have told me that, Dryden.
你已经跟我说过了，戴丹
And I want an ordinary job, sir.
我要一份普通的工作
That's my reason for resigning.
那是我辞职的原因
It's personal.
是因为私人的因素
- Personal? - Yes, sir.
- 私人的因素？ - 是的，长官
Personal? You're a serving officer in the field.
私人的因素？ 你可是一名公职军官
And as it happens, a damned important one. Are you mad?
事实上你是一个 很重要的人物，你疯了吗？
No, and if you don't mind, I'd rather not go mad.
不，如果你不介意的话 我不想发疯
That's my reason too.
那也是我的理由
Look, I'm making my big push on Damascus the 16th of next month...
听着，下个月十六号 我在大马士革有个大计划
...and you are part of it.
你是其中的一部份
Can you understand that? You're an important part of the big push!
你明白吗？你是一个 大计划中重要的一部份！
I don't want to be part of your big push!
我不要成为你的大计划中的一部份！
What about your Arab friends?
那么你的阿拉伯朋友呢？
I have no Arab friends! I don't want Arab friends!
我没有阿拉伯朋友！ 我不要阿拉伯朋友！
What in hell do you want, Lawrence?
你到底要什么？劳伦斯
I've told you, I just want my ration of common humanity.
我说过了，我只想当个普通人
- Lawrence. - Yes?
- 劳伦斯 - 什么？
Nothing. Sorry I interrupted, sir.
没什么，抱歉打断你们了
That's all right. Thank you, Mr. Dryden.
没关系，谢谢你，戴丹先生
Thank you, sir.
谢谢你
Why don't we...?
我们为什么不…？
There's blood on your back.
你背上有血
- Do you want a doctor? - No.
- 你要看医生吗？ - 不必了
Tell me what happened.
告诉我发生了什么事
Say, what goes on in there?
哎呀，那里发生了什么事？
- Nothing. - Oh, come on!
- 没什么 - 少来了！
- No, really. Nothing at all. - Is the man in trouble?
- 真的没什么，什么事都没有 - 他有麻烦了吗？
I expect so. We all have troubles. Life's a vale of troubles.
应该如此，我们都有麻烦 生活充满了麻烦
Let me know if the man's in trouble. I've got a claim in that man.
他有麻烦就告诉我 我得保护他
- What claim? - I've made that boy a hero.
- 为什么？ - 我让那孩子成了英雄
When the war's over, he can be anything he wants.
当战争结束后 他想做什么都可以
Yes. Well, at the moment he wants to be somebody else.
是，现在他想当别人
Will you kindly allow me to pass?
麻烦借过一下，好吗？
Walk away, Dryden, walk away.
逃避吧，戴丹
Always walking away, aren't you?
总是在逃避，不是吗？
Well, I'll tell you.
告诉你吧
It's a clash of temperament that's going on in there.
那里正在爆发脾气上的冲突
Inevitably, one of them's half- mad...
不可避免地他们有一个半疯了
...and the other, wholly unscrupulous.
一个完全寡廉鲜耻
I believe your name will be a household word...
我相信你的名字将会家喻户晓
...when you'd have to go to the war museum to find who Allenby was.
而要知道谁是艾伦比 还要去战争博物馆查
You're the most extraordinary man I ever met.
你是我见过最不凡的人
Leave me alone.
别来烦我
- Leave me alone. - That's a feeble thing to say.
- 别来烦我 - 真软弱的句子
- I know I'm not ordinary. - That's not what I'm saying.
- 我知道我不平凡 - 我不是那个意思
All right, I'm extraordinary.
好吧，我很不凡
What of it?
那又怎么样？
Not many people have a destiny, Lawrence.
不是很多人都注定好要成为伟人的 劳伦斯
It's a terrible thing for a man to flunk it if he has.
注定该成为伟大的人却感到害怕 那真的是太糟糕了
Are you speaking from experience?
这是你的经验谈吗？
No.
不是
You're guessing, then.
那么是你的猜测
Suppose you're wrong.
我猜你错了
Why suppose that? We both know I'm right.
你为什么会那么说？ 我们都知道我是对的
- Yes. I said, yes. - After all...
- 对，我说对 - 毕竟…
- The 16th? - Can you do it?
- 十六号？ - 你办得到吗？
I'll give you a lot of money.
我会给你很多钱
- Artillery? - I can't.
- 大炮呢？ - 我办不到
They won't be coming for money, not the best of them.
他们要的不是钱 他们当中的豪杰不是那么想的
They'll be coming for Damascus.
他们要的是大马士革
Which I'm going to give them.
我会给他们大马士革
That's all I want.
那是我想要的
All you want is someone holding down the Turkish Right.
你要我们夺走土耳其人的权利
But I'm going to give them Damascus. We'll get there before you do.
但我会给他们大马士革的 我们会抢在你们之前赶到
And when we've got it, we'll keep it.
我们夺下它之后就要留下它
Tell the politicians to burn their paper now.
叫那些政客现在烧了他们的合约
Fair enough.
很公平
Fair? What's fair got to do with it?
公平？公平与此事何干？
It's going to happen.
这是会发生的
I shall want quite a lot of money.
我要很多钱
All there is.
所有的钱都是你的
Not that much.
不要那么多
The best of them won't come for money.
他们的当中的豪杰不是要钱的
They'll come for me.
他们要的是我
No pictures!
别拍照！
It's not for you, it's for Major Lawrence.
不是要拍你，是要拍劳伦斯
He doesn't mind having his picture taken. He doesn't mind at all.
他不介意拍照 他一点都不介意
Well, there's only one Lawrence.
全世界只有一个劳伦斯
Have you met Major Lawrence since he's come back?
劳伦斯回来后 你跟他见过面吗？
Yes.
见过
- Changed, hasn't he? - No.
- 他变了，对吗？ - 没有
Oh, I'd say he had. Different man, I'd say.
我说他变了 他变成一个不一样的人了
What did that Turkish general do to him in Deraa?
那个土耳其将军在迪拉对他做了什么？
He was the same man after Deraa. The same man, humbled.
他在离开迪拉后还是一样 他只是谦卑了
What did the English general do to him in Jerusalem?
英国人在耶路撒冷对他做了什么？
Search me. Ask Lawrence.
考倒我了，去问劳伦斯吧
- I did. - What did he say?
- 我问过了 - 他怎么说？
He laughed.
他大笑
He told me to gather the Harith here.
他要我把哈利斯人叫来
He offered me money.
他还付我钱
Did you take it?
你拿了吗？
No. But many did.
没有，但很多人拿了
- What is this? - This is my bodyguard.
- 这是什么？ - 这是我的保镖
There is not a man without a price on his head.
这里每个人的人头都是有价格的
- There's a price on my head too. - But these are murderers.
- 我的人头也有价格 - 但他们是杀手
The sheiks will hang these men.
酋长会吊死这些人的
These men are mine.
他们是我的人
Lawrence, these things know nothing of the Arab revolt.
劳伦斯，他们不了解阿拉伯叛乱
- You, Ghitan of Aleppo. - Sherif?
- 你，艾拉波的盖坦 - 长官？
- Where do we ride? - Damascus, sherif.
- 我们要往哪里去啊？ - 大马士革，长官
Aye, but for what?
对，但为什么？
Sherif, for Lawrence.
沙利夫，为了劳伦斯
- You have bought these things. - I bought half the men here, Ali.
- 你买下了这些东西 - 我买下这里一半的人，阿里
That is different. These are not ordinary men.
那不一样，他们不是普通人
I don't want ordinary men. Hut!
我不要普通人，走吧！
Damascus!
大马士革！
Damascus! Damascus!
大马士革！…
Very well, gentlemen. The cavalry's gone through Mazril and Deraa.
各位，骑兵队通过犸兹瑞尔跟迪拉了
Very good, by the way. Very good indeed. Now your turn.
这真的是非常好，轮到你们了
If the enemy's retreating in any order, which we'll assume...
如果敌人撤退 我们知道他们会撤退的…
Certainly.
当然
He can't be far from Mallud...
他不会离麦拉德太远
...in which case I can have him within range by 0900 hours tomorrow.
所以我应该 在明天九点前能看到他
Splendid. Philip.
太棒了，菲立普
These are the last infantry supports going up now.
这是现阶段最后的步兵支援部队
But Mallud, we could have the fusiliers there by Wednesday.
但星期三燧发枪团会到麦拉德
That'll do for now. The guns are what matter.
现在那样就够了，重要的是枪
Any questions?
有问题吗？
This Arab army on the right, sir, what's it consist of?
这只阿拉伯军队在右边 它是什么组成的？
Irregular cavalry, sir. About 2000.
非正式的骑兵队 大约有两千人
Where are they now?
他们现在在哪里？
- Can only know by being with them. - Then get with them. I want to know.
- 跟他们在一起的人才知道 - 那么去找他们，我要知道
Pound them, Charley.
痛击他们，查利
Pound them.
痛击他们
God help the men who lie under that.
愿主保佑躺在那下面的人
They're Turks.
他们是土耳其人
God help them.
愿主保佑他们
Well, he's got the bit between his teeth all right.
他简直是失去控制
Cocky?
他很傲慢吗？
More than cocky, sir.
不光只是傲慢而已
He's got the bit between his teeth all right.
他简直是失去控制
I tell you, sir, I think he'll get to Damascus before we do.
我告诉你 我想他会比我们早到大马士革
- Unless... - Unless?
- 除非… - 除非？
Well, there's a Turkish column in front of him, out of Mazril.
在犸兹瑞尔外 有一队土耳其人挡在他前面
- What do the Turks have in Mazril? - A brigade, sir.
- 犸兹瑞尔有多少土耳其军队？ - 有一旅
I wonder where they are now.
不知道他们现在在哪里
No prisoners.
不准有囚犯
Damascus, Lawrence.
大马士革，劳伦斯
Lawrence, not this.
劳伦斯，别这样
Go round. Damascus, Lawrence, Damascus.
来吧，大马士革，劳伦斯
No prisoners.
通通杀光
This was Talaal's village.
这以前是塔拉尔人的村落
Talaal!
塔拉尔人！
No prisoners!
通通杀光！
God.
天啊
God!
天啊！
Enough. Enough! Make them stop!
够了，叫他们住手！
Major!
少校！
Major Lawrence!
劳伦斯少校！
Jesus wept.
老天爷啊
Does it surprise you, Mr. Bentley?
那令你惊讶吗？班特利先生
Surely you know the Arabs are a barbarous people.
你知道阿拉伯人是一只野蛮民族
Barbarous and cruel.
野蛮又残忍
Who but they?
除了他们还会是谁？
Oh, you rotten man.
你这个混蛋
Here, let me take your rotten bloody picture.
来吧，我帮你这个混蛋拍张照
For the rotten bloody newspapers.
给那个该死的报纸
These were cut last night, Lawrence, in Damascus.
这是昨晚在大马士革割下来的 劳伦斯
Damascus!
大马士革！
Take them to Sherif Ali.
把它们拿去给阿里长官
Tell him.
告诉他
Remind him.
提醒他
- Is Allenby in Damascus? - Near.
- 艾伦比在大马士革吗？ - 他在附近
Tell Sherif Ali that.
告诉阿里长官
They are not ripe.
他们还没熟呢
(大马士革)
General salute!
将军万岁！
Present arms!
举枪！
Port arms!
枪放下！
Lawrence is behind it, sir.
劳伦斯在背后搞鬼，长官
The whole town is plastered with the Arab flag.
全镇贴满了阿拉伯旗帜
- When? - A day and a night, sir.
- 那是什么时候的事？ - 已经一天一夜，长官
They've been here a day and a night.
他们来这里一天一夜了
They've occupied the town. They've done it.
他们占据了这个小镇 他们做到了
He's set up his own headquarters in the town hall.
他将总部设在镇公所
What else beside the town hall?
除了镇公所外还占了什么？
Telephone exchange, post office, powerhouse...
电信局，邮局，发电厂…
...hospitals, fire station. Everything, sir.
医院，火车站 什么都占了，长官
They call themselves the Arab National Council...
他们自称是阿拉伯国家议会
...and they're in the town hall.
他们在镇公所里
Well, they're your pigeon, Harry.
他们是你的问题了，哈利
What should we do about it?
我们该怎么办？
Get them out of it, sir, quick time.
尽快把他们弄出那里
How about that, Dryden?
你觉得呢？戴丹
Not unless you want a full- scale rising.
除非你想引起全面的抗争
- What, then? - When will Feisal be in Damascus?
- 那么要怎么做呢？ - 费瑟何时会到大马士革？
By special train in two days' time.
他搭专用的火车，两天内会到
Two days.
两天
Two days is what you asked for. I can't keep him out any longer.
最多两天，超过了 我无法再拖住他
- Isn't it enough? - Yes.
- 那不够吗？ - 够了
- Ample, I should think. - We can't just do nothing.
- 我想够了 - 我们不能什么都不做
Why not? It's usually best. Get us something to drink, Tracey.
为什么？通常那是最好的方法 拿点东西来给我们喝，崔西
And Tracey, all troops to remain quartered until further orders.
崔西，没有进一步的命令 军队们都扎营不准离开
Does that apply to technical units?
技术单位也一样吗？
Technical units particularly.
特别是技术单位
Yes, sir.
是的，长官
Medicals too, sir?
医药单位也一样吗？长官
I'm afraid so, Harry.
恐怕是的，哈利
Medicals too.
医药单位也一样
We here...
这里的人…
...are neither Harith nor Howeitat...
不是哈利斯人或哈威塔特人
...nor any other tribe, but Arabs...
也不是其他部族的人
...of the Arab Council, acting for Prince Feisal.
我们是费瑟王子 领导的阿拉伯议会的阿拉伯人
He insulted me.
他侮辱我
Sherif Ali said that the telephones are in the care of the Howeitat...
阿里长官说 电话现在属于哈威塔特人
...and they have ceased to work. And this is true.
它们现在都不通，这是真的
They will not work because they are given no electricity.
电话不通是因为没电
The electricity is in the care of the Harith.
电属于哈利斯人
If you answer, there will be bloodshed.
你一答话，就会血流成河
You speak to me of bloodshed?
你要跟我谈血流成河？
I ask pardon of Auda Abu Tayi.
我请求奥达阿布塔耶的原谅
Humbly?
诚心的求吗？
Humbly, Harith?
诚心的求吗？哈利斯
Yes, humbly.
是的，诚心的求
This is a new trick.
这倒是新把戏
Why is there no electricity?
为什么没电？
I have been to that electrical house, Lawrence.
我去过发电厂了，劳伦斯
There are three large machines.
那里有三部大机器
He means generators!
他是说发电机！
So.
所以呢？
One of them is burning.
有一部在燃烧
They are of an incredible size, but helpless.
所有机器都是这样
It is so of all machines.
Let them burn. What need of telephones?
由它们烧吧，电话有什么作用？
- The need is absolute. - Then we need English engineers.
- 当然有用 - 那么我们需要英国工程师
No. Take English engineers and you take English government.
不，把英国工程师带进来 英国政府也会跟着来
Take...
带…
Fire has broken out.
失火了
- Where? - The Jinsibi district.
- 在哪里？ - 金西比区
- It is not a district that matters. - It will spread!
- 在那一区不重要 - 火势会扩散的！
Then use the fire brigade!
那么叫消防队啊！
We have tried, but there is no force in the water.
我们试过了，但水不够强
Then you must carry it.
那你们得去提水
- The Ruala do not carry water. - What else are they good for?
- 鲁阿拉人不提水的 - 他们会做什么事？
We will hear petitions this afternoon.
我们今天下午才接受陈情
This afternoon!
今天下午！
- I'll take this up after the war. - Surely we should do something, sir.
- 战后我要面对这些事 - 我们真的该想个办法啊
- It's an old man's sport. - Are you an old man, sir?
- 这是老人的运动了 - 你是老人吗？
All I can say is, sir, it's a heavy responsibility.
我只能说责任真的很重大
Sorry, sir.
对不起
Maybe it's the bulb.
或许是灯泡的问题
No, sir.
不是的
It's the power.
是电力的问题
They're leaving.
他们要离开了
That's it, then.
那么就这样了
Marvellous- Iooking beggars, aren't they?
他们这些乞丐长得不错，对吧？
Leave it, Lawrence. Come with me.
算了吧，劳伦斯，跟我来
- Come where? - Back.
- 去哪里？ - 回去
I know your heart.
我了解你的心
What is it?
那是什么？
Is it this?
是这个吗？
I tell you, this is nothing.
我说过了，这没什么
Is it the blood?
那是血吗？
The desert has dried up more blood than you could think of.
在沙漠里流干的血 比你想像中还多
I pray that I may never see the desert again.
我祈祷再也不必去沙漠
Hear me, God.
听我说，上帝
You will come. There is only the desert for you.
你会来的 沙漠是你唯一栖身之处
What about you?
你呢？
No, I shall stay here and learn politics.
不，我要待在这里学习政治
A very low occupation.
一种很低等的职业
I had not thought of it when I met you.
我在遇见你时 根本没想过要这样
You have tried very hard to give us Damascus.
你非常努力地 将大马士革交给我们
It's what I came for.
那是我来这里的原因
And then...
那么…
...it would be something.
那是件伟大的事
Yes.
对
Much.
很伟大
- He is your friend? - Take your hand away.
- 他是你的朋友吗？ - 把你的手拿开
- You love him. - I fear him.
- 你爱他 - 我怕他
Then why do you weep?
那你为什么哭？
If I fear him, who love him...
如果我怕他，也那么爱他…
...how must he fear himself, who hates himself?
就知道他有多怕自己 多么的痛恨自己的了？
Take your hand away, Howeitat!
把你的手拿开，哈威塔特人！
So you are not yet entirely politician.
原来你还不是一个完全的政客
Not yet.
还不是
Well, these are new tricks, and I am an old dog.
现在有很多新把戏 而我是一只老狗了
And Allah be thanked.
谢谢阿拉
I'll tell thee what...
我会告诉你…
...being an Arab will be thornier than you suppose, Harith.
当一个阿拉伯人 比你想像中还难，哈利斯
In all my years, I've never seen anything like it.
我一生没看过这种事
It comes within the jurisdiction of the Arab Council.
这是阿拉伯议会的管辖范围？
Under the circumstances, I think I must take over. Immediately.
在这种情况下 我想我该立刻接手
Under any circumstances at all, you must obey your orders.
毕竟在任何一种情况下 你都该服从命令
No, sir, I will not.
不，长官，我不会的
Control yourself.
控制一下你自己
Now, go over to the town hall and see what they say.
到镇公所那边 去看看他们说了什么
We did what we could in the civic hospitals.
市立医院那边已经尽力了
But you forgot the Turkish Military Hospital.
但你忘了土耳其军事医院
It has 600 beds. There are about 2000 Turkish wounded in it.
那里有六百个床位 有约两千名的土耳其伤患
All of whom are the responsibility of your precious Arab Council.
他们都是你宝贝的阿拉伯议会的责任
What's it like?
情形是如何呢？
This is outrageous!
这太过份了！
Outrageous!
太过份了！
You filthy little wog!
你这个王八蛋！
My friend Lawrence, if I may call him that.
“我的朋友劳伦斯” 如果我可以这么叫他的话
"My friend Lawrence."
“我的朋友劳伦斯”
How many men will claim the right to use that phrase? How proudly.
多少人会宣称 他们有权那么说呢？太光荣了
He longs for the greenness of his native land.
他期盼着祖国的绿地
He pines for the Gothic cottages of Surrey, is it not?
他渴望在苏利的葛德式房屋，对吧？
Already in imagination, he catches trout...
他已经在想像他钓着鳟鱼
...and all the activities of the English gentleman.
从事英国绅士的所有活动
That's me you're describing, sir, not Colonel Lawrence.
你说的人是我 不是劳伦斯上校
You're promoted colonel.
你升上上校了
Yes. What for?
是，为什么？
Take the honour, colonel. Be a little kind.
接受这荣誉吧，上校 表现出一点热忱来
As a colonel, you'll have a cabin to yourself on the boat home.
身为上校，在船坞那边 你会有栋小木屋
Then, thank you.
谢谢你
Well, then...
那么…
...Godspeed.
愿上帝保佑你
There's nothing further here for a warrior.
这里不需要战士了
We drive bargains. Old men's work.
我们在讨价还价 那是老头子的工作
Young men make wars, and the virtues of war...
年青人制造战争 战争的本质…
...are the virtues of young men.
就是年轻人的本质
Courage and hope for the future.
未来的勇气跟希望
Then old men make the peace.
老人则维持和平
And the vices of peace are the vices of old men.
和平的罪行是老人的罪行
Mistrust and caution.
不信任跟戒心
It must be so.
一定是这样的
What I owe you is beyond evaluation.
我欠你的东西多到数不清
The powerhouse, the telephone exchange, these I concede.
发电厂，电信局，这些我都认输
The pumping plant I must retain.
我得留住水厂
If you retain it, there will be no water.
如果你留住了它 那么就无水可用了
- I shall be glad of assistance. - Then you must bring down your flag.
- 我很希望你们能够帮忙 - 那么你得扯下你的旗帜
I shall not, and if your men attempt it, my men will resist it.
我不会的，若你手下要那么做 我的手下会反抗的
- Have you men? - Enough of that.
- 你有手下吗？ - 我的手下够打败你了
It's a thing that makes an ugly incident.
这件事可以造成了可怕的事件
I'm sure your government...
我相信你的政府…
...does not wish to appear at the peace conference as an aggressor.
不希望在和平会议上 以侵略者的身份出现
I say!
喂！
It's Lawrence, isn't it?
是劳伦斯，对吧？
May I shake your hand, sir?
我能跟您握个手吗？
Just want to be able to say I'd done it, sir.
我只是想跟别人吹嘘一下而已
Haven't we met before?
我们以前不认识吧？
Don't think so, sir.
我想是不认识
No, no, sir, I should remember that.
对，不然我会记得的
It is widely known the Arab Council took power in my name.
大家都知道阿拉伯议会 是因我之名而得到权力
They have no power. It's illusory.
他们没有权力，那是错觉
Illusions can be very powerful.
错觉有时会很有力的
Particularly...
特别是…
...when they take this form.
当它们采取这样的模式
The world is delighted at the picture of Damascus...
全世界都很喜欢…
...liberated by the Arab army.
被阿拉伯军队 解放大马士革的照片
Led, may I remind you, by a British- serving officer.
我得提醒你，那次行动 是由一位英国军官所领导
Ah, yes. But then Lawrence is a sword with two edges.
对，劳伦斯 像是一把刀的两面利刃
We are equally glad to be rid of him, are we not?
我们都很高兴除掉他了，对吧？
I thought I was a hard man, sir.
我还以为我是个狠心人
You are merely a general.
你只是一个将军
I must be a king.
我该当个国王的
Excuse me, sir.
对不起
Well?
什么？
Well...
那个…
...it seems we're to have a British waterworks...
看来我们将会有一个 插上了阿拉伯旗帜的…
...with an Arab flag on it.
英国水利局
Do you think it was worth it?
你觉得值得吗？
Not my business. Thank God I'm a soldier.
那不关我的事 谢天谢地，我是个士兵
Yes, sir.
是的
So you keep saying.
你一直都是那么说
You, I suspect...
我猜…
...are chief architect of this compromise.
你是这个大和解的主要推手
- What do you think? - Me, Your Highness?
- 你觉得呢？ - 我吗？殿下
On the whole, I wish I'd stayed in Tunbridge Wells.
总体来说 我后悔离开唐布利吉水井区
Well, sir. Going home.
回家去吧
Home, sir.
Goodbye, Dolly, I must leave you
再见，多丽，我得离开你
Though it breaks my heart to go
虽然离去会让我心伤